<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charity enlarged: or The abridgement of the morall law Delivered by way of sermon, and preached for the maine substance thereof in a publicke assembly, on a lecture day, Dec. 4. Ao. Dom. 1634. and now published according to the authors review, with some new additions, for the farther instruction of the ignorant, satisfaction of the ingenuous, conviction of the uncharitable, and benefit of all sorts of people. By a serious welwisher to the peace of Ierusalem.</title>
            <author>Serious welwisher to the peace of Jerusalem.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854325</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19741</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1342:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charity enlarged: or The abridgement of the morall law Delivered by way of sermon, and preached for the maine substance thereof in a publicke assembly, on a lecture day, Dec. 4. Ao. Dom. 1634. and now published according to the authors review, with some new additions, for the farther instruction of the ignorant, satisfaction of the ingenuous, conviction of the uncharitable, and benefit of all sorts of people. By a serious welwisher to the peace of Ierusalem.</title>
                  <author>Serious welwisher to the peace of Jerusalem.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 204 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. C[otes] for T. A[lchorn] and are to be sold at the Greene Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1636]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19741:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19741:1"/>
            <p>CHARITY ENLARGED: OR THE ABRIDGEMENT of the Morall Law. Delivered by way of Sermon, and preached for the maine ſubſtance thereof in a publicke aſſembly, on a Lecture day, <hi>Dec.</hi> 4. <hi>A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Dom.</hi> 1634. and now publiſhed according to the Authors review, with ſome new additions, for the farther inſtruction of the ignorant, ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ingenuous, conviction of the uncharitable, and benefit of all ſorts of people.</p>
            <p>By a ſerious welwiſher to the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ſmall and deſpiſed yet have I not forgotten thy Law.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſal. <hi>119.141.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Damnatus alijs, ipſe neminem damno. <bibl>H. Gr.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Damus Dei credendo fundatur, ſperando erigitur, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo perficitur. <bibl>Aug. Serm. <hi>20.</hi> de verb. Apoſt.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>London printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>T. A.</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Greene-Dragon</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:19741:2"/>
            <p>Perlegi tractatum hunc, cui titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus <hi>Charity enlarged, &amp;c.</hi> in quo nihil reperio ſanae fidei, aut bonis moribus contrarium.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Weekes R.P. Epi. Lond. Cap. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19741:2"/>
            <head>CHARITIE ENLARGED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.</hi> ver. <hi>10. The latter part of the</hi> verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>Therefore love is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning which words, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, if you looke for any artificiall connexion, or diviſion, or deduction to be propoſed unto you. For the firſt, know, that <hi>love</hi> it ſelfe is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19741:3"/> Copulative, and unites all good duties. In this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is well conjoyned to obedience unto Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, whether Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall or civill: For they may well give feare to whom feare is neceſſary, but they will never give true honour to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is due, who give not <hi>love</hi> to whom <hi>love</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth<note n="a" place="margin">Hierom. Epiſt. ad Dominio.</note> 
               <hi>Horum enim potentiae non parcunt ſed cedunt,</hi> For they doe not ſpare, <hi>Iude</hi> 8. to ſpeake evill of dignities, at leaſt in the dialect of their thoughts, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle of their hearts, where their rebellious imaginations aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the Lord and his annointed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19741:3"/> 
               <hi>Let us (Pſal.</hi> 2.3.) <hi>breake their bands, &amp;c.</hi> of feare, as wee have broken thoſe of <hi>love:</hi> it is onely the conſciouſneſſe of their owne weakeneſſe to reſiſt authority,<note n="b" place="margin">They ſpare not ſo much o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers as them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves. As <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pollinaris</hi> repli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to his Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peror deſiring to be ſpared in a Satyre which hee wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compoſing. <hi>Quod ab illici tis te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pero mihi parco:</hi> but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> inhibits even diſloyall thoughts <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> which makes them not for conſcience, but neceſſities ſake to yeeld ſubjection.<note n="c" place="margin">Metus &amp; terror infirma vincula chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſunt quae ubi removeris quitimere deſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent odiſſe inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient. Tacit. in vita Iulij A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricolae.</note> Hence as their feare ebbs, their malice flowes, as the one is abated the other is increaſed; even as when one bucket comes up another goes downe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>love</hi> admits of no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion from the <hi>Law,</hi> nor the <hi>Law</hi> of any ſeparation from <hi>Love.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Amor eſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus umonis Scal. <hi>Exc.</hi> 301.</note> 
               <hi>Love</hi> hates partition, it is the grace which makes brethren live together,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>in uno,</hi> in one, or <hi>in unitate,</hi> in unity it ſelfe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19741:4"/> in the abſtract, and if it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate their habitation, (as in the caſe of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi>) yet it unites their hearts more and more, ſo that when they are fartheſt aſunder, then they are nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt together;<note n="3" place="margin">So the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammatiſt ſaith of his ill neighbour, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Epig.</hi> 87. <hi>Nemo tam prope tam proculve nobis.</hi>
               </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as malicious cohabitants, though incloſed within the ſame walls are moſt diſtant the one from the other. Laſtly, the text it ſelfe is a Doctrinall concluſion, and implies no other propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but its owne premiſes, in which are vertually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all the doctrines of practicall piety. This is the abrogation of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, and the abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Morall Law. For Love is that <hi>Verbum
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19741:4"/> abbreviatum quod faciet Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ſuper terram,</hi> in Saint <hi>Hieromes</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In Iſa. c <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Expoſition <hi>ſc.</hi> the tedious ceremonies of the Law, being gathered into the precept of <hi>love,</hi> as into a ſhort ſumme with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. And the<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 9.28.</note> whole Morall <hi>Law</hi> too, as the Apoſtle phraſeth it in the <hi>verſe</hi> before my text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is recapitulated or briefely comprehended in <hi>love,</hi> and fulfilled by <hi>love</hi> in the text: ſo that if you be of the ſame minde concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this precept of which<note n="e" place="margin">Socrat. Eccl. Hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pambo</hi> was in reſpect of <hi>Davids</hi> reſolve, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. <hi>ſc.</hi> not to take any new leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of inſtruction out of Gods Word, untill you have learned this perfectly,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19741:5"/> not onely at your tongues ends to talke of it, but at your fingers ends to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid enim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erba audio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a cum uideam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ug. ſc. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aria verbis?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo many are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iers, <hi>in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. hiſt. pa.</hi> 19. <hi>Lingua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roris ignavi,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir charity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke a limon, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot in the rine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the outſide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut cold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n or at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart.</note> you ſhall not onely with him ſpend nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares, but your whole lives to the longeſt day in the ſtudy of this one word <hi>Love.</hi> There is a uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtory, and not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable in the<note n="k" place="margin">In Galat. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Coment aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed unto Saint <hi>Hierome;</hi> in which it is related, that when Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> by reaſon of old age, was not able to make any long diſcourſe unto his diſciples, he would oft repeate that precept of <hi>love,</hi> which is in effect the ſumme of his three Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>My little children love one another:</hi> and when ſome of his Schollers deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19741:5"/> of new matter, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a reaſon why hee ſo oft inculcated the ſame thing into their mindes, he anſwered, <hi>Quia preceptum Domini eſt, &amp; ſi ſolum fiat ſufficit:</hi> becauſe it is Chriſts Commandement, and if it alone be performed, it is enough. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo witneſſeth, ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Love is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of which words I ſhall bee conducted by this method, 1. You ſhall heare the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the termes ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that you may learne what is underſtood, by <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>Law,</hi> or the <hi>fulfilling of the Law.</hi> 2. I ſhall confirme or illuſtrate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19741:6"/> the concluſion, with a few teſtimonies out of the Scriptures and Fathers. 3. I ſhall diſtinctly declare unto you the ſeverall wayes, and reſpects, according to which <hi>love,</hi> fulfils the <hi>Law.</hi> 4. And laſtly, I ſhall apply to practiſe what I have conſidered in ſpeculation. 1. What <hi>love</hi> is, learne from Saint <hi>Aug. de doct. Chriſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Charitatem voco motum animi ad fruendum Deo propter ipſum, &amp; ſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que proximo, propter deum.</hi> I call charity a motion or moving of the minde,<note place="margin">What love is.</note> to enjoy God for his owne ſake, a mans ſelfe, and his neighbour for Gods ſake; and ſo conſequently to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all good to God and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19741:6"/> man; as to God, the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his glory, to man, the participation of divine goodneſſe. And thus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here comprehends both the love of God and of man. And ſemblably this terme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, compriſeth both the tables of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Pareus An. Willet. Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtius.</note> although in the 8. <hi>verſe,</hi> and elſe where it implies onely the ſecond Table. So that by the judgement of learned Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors; Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> logicke runs thus. If the love of our neighbour (as I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>verſe</hi> the 8. and 9.) fulfill the Law in reſpect of thoſe duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our neighbour, then love in its full extenſion as it tends to its univerſall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19741:7"/> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> both God and all good men, doth fulfil the whole <hi>Law.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Charitas nunquam otioſa eſt ſemper in alterum ſe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigit, vel in proximum vel in Deum. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura enim chae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis eſt &amp; amare velle, &amp; velle amari. Caſſiodo. tract. de ami.</hi> Well then doth S. <hi>Aug.</hi> call cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity a motion, becauſe it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is at a ſtand: Shee ſtretcheth forth her armes continually to embrace God, or her neighbour, and puts forth her hands to doe what good ſhe can to both. Her reſtleſſe deſires are, to love and to be loved.</note> For love is a like diſpoſed to fulfill the precepts of both Tables, as of either.<note n="n" place="margin">Fides non eligit objectum, ſecundùm Theologos ſed omnibus revelatis ſine exceptione crediti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta charitas non eligit praeceptii quodexequatur, ad omnia &amp; ſingula parata eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cum la lio apud Lucan. l, clamat (ſe Domino &amp; imperatori ſuo alacriler devovens.) Iuſſa ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui tam vella mihi quam poſſe neceſſe eſt.</note> Yea Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhewes that wee cannot keepe the one Table, and breake the other, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not love our God, and hate our brethren, which are made after the Image of God. Hee who loves the father loves the children (though full of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) for the fathers ſake, as <hi>David</hi> ſhewed favour to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19741:7"/> lame <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> for the memory of his <hi>Ionathan;</hi> muchleſſe can wee truely love our brethren, and hate our God. Doth any man delight to behold the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of his mortall enemy. <hi>If any man, (then)</hi> ſaith he, <hi>love God, and hate his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is a lyer,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20. Loe what a lyer is hee that proteſts hee loves his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet hates God. For the love of man is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the love of God, as the effect in the cauſe;<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke 10.27.</hi> Toto corde <hi>i. e.</hi> vere, tota anime <hi>i. e.</hi> affect. bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cunctis, totis viribus <hi>i. e</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, tota mente <hi>i. e.</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenter.</note> ſo that <hi>love</hi> is the fulfilling of the firſt Table directly and immediatly, of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond mediatly, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as ſhall in its place be evidenced unto you.</p>
            <p>In the meane time if any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19741:8"/> one having ſome compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knowledge of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires more fully to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how hee is to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, let him meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Deutero.</hi> 6.5. Then if hee aske who is his neighbour,<note place="margin">Who is our neighbour.</note> and how hee is to be loved, hee nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not goe farre for inſtruction. Him whom our Apoſtle calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>proximum,</hi> one that is neere unto thee, thy neighbour in my Text, and in the precedent <hi>verſe:</hi> hee calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. another, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſides thy ſelfe, whether neere to thee, or a farre off, whether friend or adverſary, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther familiar or ſtranger,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19741:8"/> whether of thy kindred, or alliance, or neither, whether beleever or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleever: In a word, any one whoſoever, that in any reſpect whatſoever, ſtands in neede of thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable deedes or prayers, or that ſhewes any kinde of charity unto thee, God onely excepted as<note n="p" place="margin">Is eſt proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cui vel ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibendum eſt officium miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae ſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digit, vel exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum ſoret ſi indigeret: ex quo iam conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, ut etiam ille aquo nobis hoc viſſim ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibendum eſt (quod ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos etiam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet) proximus ſit noster. Proximus enim eſt nomen ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, aliquid nec quiſquam eſſe proximus, niſi proximo poteſt Aug. de doct. Chriſt. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>30</hi> &amp; ex eo Lomb. l. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>Lombard</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>So our Saviour plainely informes us by the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the wounded travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt, de doct. Christ. l. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> which may alſo be gathered by an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argumentation from the precepts which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the love of our neighbour, ſome of which our Apoſtle reckons up,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19741:9"/> 
               <hi>verſe</hi> 9.<note n="r" place="margin">Manifeſtum eſt omnem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem eſſe prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imum deputan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quia erga neminem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum eſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Dilectio. enim proximi malum non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur.</note> If there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man that were not our neighbour in the ſence of the Law, hee ſhould not offend againſt the law of charity, comprehended in the ſecond Table, who ſhould robbe ſuch a man of his goods or good name, yea, or ſpoile him of his very life,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.10.</note> and ſo there might be done, as much and more by Law, as Iſrael did to the Egyptians by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine diſpenſation.<note place="margin">Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſinners.</note> A point which ſome mens unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe may perhaps admit; accounting any gaine of wealth or eſteeme from all thoſe whom they judge as Heathens and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, to be no leſſe godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to them, than uſury
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19741:9"/> was to the Iew from a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanite. But the conſcience of charity is not ſo large, her extention is in good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards all. A man of right charity will draw neere in love and affection to thoſe who are a farre off from him in kindred or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation; although thoſe who are neere to him by conſanguinity or place are a farre off from him in their hearts. Yea, he is neere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in his private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and in his good wiſhes, who are a farre off from him in Religion, or goodneſſe, which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry object of love: But cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can ſuppoſe an object when ſhe wants one, and ſupply that by deſires
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19741:10"/> which is not in reality, and affect that in poſſibility which is not in act exiſtent. 1. Shee can hide the leſſer errors or ſinnes of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. 2. She can excuſe them with <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 3.17.3. When they are ſo groſſe that no excuſe can extenuate them<note n="ſ" place="margin">Yea ſuppoſing we may know that one hath committed the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt. Charitie can be ſorry for ſuch a man. <hi>Si non propter hominem ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men propter hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatem;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe be not permitted to pray for him, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.16. She is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence which may not be prayed for. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as wee cut not of rotten members whilſt there is any h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and when they muſt be cut off, we part from them with griefe of heart, and wiſh wee might have kept them. So <hi>Samuel</hi> alſo mourned for <hi>Saul</hi> forſaken of God, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 15 <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> ſhee will not ceaſe to pray or hope for amendment, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. <hi>As for mee, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that I ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord in ceaſing to pray for you.</hi> And chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as ſhee deſireth, ſo ſhee hopeth all things, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. So farre is ſhe from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19741:10"/> wiſhing or curſing any into the bottomleſſe pit, that ſhee can ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.7. in the caſe of any good ſhe enjoyeth, <hi>I would that all men were even as I my ſelf.</hi> Shee laments or pitties the furious malice of the Papiſts, damning all Proteſtants with one mouth, and the parallell raſhneſſe of ſome ſort of Proteſtants damning all Papiſts, and ſpeaking evill of thoſe of their owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion alſo, which will not runne with them into the ſame exceſſe of zeale, but preferre even the errour of charity before the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory cenſure of thoſe that erre. Away with theſe damning (I had almoſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19741:11"/> thence learned the phraſe of damned, but I ſay) and juſtly condemned cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: For if theſe ſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Who then ſhall be ſaved,</hi> as the Apoſtles aske Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.25. Let it be the glory of our Church to follow, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.19. truth and peace in her opinions, diſcretion and charity in her cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. In her controverſies (which muſt needs be that truth may be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, as by the colliſion of flints ſparkes of fire are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out) let her imitate <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> the Archangel diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting even with the devill, about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> not daring to bring any rayling accuſation againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19741:11"/> him, but ſaying, onely, <hi>the Lord rebuke thee, Iude</hi> 9. Or with <hi>David: Smite the faces of thine adverſaries</hi> (the enemies of thy truth) <hi>with ſhame, that they may ſeeke thy Name, O God.</hi> Whilſt ſome of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with <hi>Martha</hi> are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with many things, with vaine ſuſpitions and feares, with uncertaine and doubtfull diſputations, and oppoſitions of ſcience falſely ſo called, with ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſcandals and errors, with envy, hatred, and all uncharitableneſſe: ſhee with <hi>Mary</hi> hath choſen the better part, the part of <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> tempering knowledge, that it puffe not up nature into any proud opinion of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19741:12"/> her owne ſelfe or cenſure of others. In the one ſhee followes Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> advice, which he calls the ſafeſt<note n="t" place="margin">Tutiores vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſi totum Deo demus citig.</note> 
               <hi>Totum (ſc. quod bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt) deo dando,</hi> attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all that is good to God, without whom man hath<note n="u" place="margin">In nullo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andum quando nihil eſt noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cypr. in Oratio. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omin.</note> no ability to thinke, much leſſe to doe good. And in the other, to wit, judgeing what is unpardonably evill in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>totum deo relinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> leaving it wholy to God, and hoping the beſt that may be: For though the concluſion of Logicke and malice follow <hi>deteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem partem;</hi> Divinity and charity embrace that part which is apparantly beſt, and leave uncertainties to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19741:12"/> Gods ſupreme determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Exod. 12.8, 9.10.</note> The Iewes were commanded to eate the fleſh of the Paſchall Lambe, and to burne the bones with fire. By faith, we eate the fleſh of Chriſt, the antitype of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and digeſt him into action by love, through which faith worketh, but hard and unprofitable que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions are to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the fire, that is, (ſaith<note n="w" place="margin">Citatus ab Eccleſ. Lugd. in lib. Reſp. ad <hi>3.</hi> Epist.</note> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi>) are to be left to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Spirit of God, which like fire manifeſts all things. In the <hi>interim</hi> charity goes a ſure and a lawfull way, teaching us to love, not onely our friends, but even our adverſaries,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19741:13"/> either in Religion or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or both: yea, this is a way not onely of ſafety but of<note n="x" place="margin">Verum ſit ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>joris perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis amicos an inimicos dilige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?</note> comparative per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection alſo, according to the opinion of divers<note n="y" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Ambroſ. Aug. Bern. Alenſis, Durand. Bona. Argentin. &amp; Lomb. in <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>30.</hi> huc trahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Schoolemen ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Fr. de Mendoca, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>virid. Probl.</hi> 4. who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the love of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be a more perfect act than the love of our friends: Which opinion they confirme by proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons:<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus ea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria paſſio eſt nobilior, quae eſt nobilioris ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ei: ſic in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus, actus perfectionis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eſt perfectior: I am lex nova, quae viviſicat, &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat, eſt nobilior quam vetus quae mortificat, &amp; gravat: Ergo. Mendoca loc. cit. ſic argumentatur.</note> as becauſe it is an act correſpondent to a more perfect law, <hi>ſc.</hi> of the new Teſtament: (For ſay they) the old Law gave way to outward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19741:13"/> to<note n="2" place="margin">Civilis ine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus eiuſdem Reipub. alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Religionis cultor, quem ex animo odiſſe non licebat, Levit. <hi>19</hi> v. <hi>17</hi> externa tamen odii ſigna per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittebantur, ut lege talionis agere, Levit. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>19.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>guinei mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ulci ſci &amp;c. ut Id. ib. urget.</note> civill enemies, and to both outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hatred towards the<note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>Legalis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us erat a Repub. Iudaica alienus, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinaelegis xors,</hi> one that was a ſtranger from the common wealth of Iſrael (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles him) and an alien from Gods Covenant of grace, with that people, as all other nations in the world were before Chriſts comming, towards whom not onely externall, but alſo (ſay ſome) internall hatred was permitted to be exerciſed, by uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, oppreſſion, utter extirpation, Deut. 7, 23, 24. and ch. 25.17, 18.19, Pſalm. 139, 21, 22.</note> legall enemies of the Iewes, ſuch as the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites were, whom they might perſecute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy.</p>
            <p>Againe, that love is more perfect which makes us more like unto God, and ſuch is the act of love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our enemies. In the love of our friends, and ſuch as are neere unto us,<note n="a" place="bottom">Mat. 5.47, What doe you more than others? &amp;c,</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what excellent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19741:14"/> thing is there, whereby we ſurpaſſe the heathen, the wicked worldling, yea, the very beaſts which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally love thoſe of the ſame kinde? But ſaith our Saviour,<note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 5.44, 45. Luke 6.35. Whence note that Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate Gods perfection; <hi>pro ſuo modulo,</hi> Matth. 5.48. And ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently they muſt excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Pro. 12.26. Matth. 5.20. Laſtly this their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy conſiſts in Charity, 1 Cor. 12.31. and 14.12.</note> 
               <hi>Love your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that you may bee like your Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Who is like unto thee O Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſweres, <hi>Qui benè vult inimico ſuo,</hi> He who beares good will to his enemie, may confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and yet not proudly ſay that he is like unto thee O Lord. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.1.3. Enquires whether there be any of the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> left, not that he may exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute upon the poſterity of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19741:14"/> his enemie any remnant of hoſtile revenge, but (ſaith he) that I may ſhew unto him the kindneſſe of God. <hi>i.e.</hi> that I may bee kind, to him as God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to his foes, cauſing the Sunne of his favour to ſhine, and the rayne of his beneficence to deſcend not onely upon the juſt, but upon the unjuſt alſo. And therefore the<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 7.2.</note> Lord ſaies that hee hath made <hi>Moſes</hi> a God to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> becauſe hee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred good for evill, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for threates and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: whereas<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 45.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is called onely a Father to the other <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who was a friend unto him, and a Benefactour. But for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19741:15"/> maine point, all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Ieſuiticall</hi> Doctor following the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of moderne Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note n="e" place="margin">Aquin. <hi>2.</hi> a. q. <hi>27.</hi> art. <hi>7.</hi> Greg. valent d. <hi>3.</hi> q <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>3.</hi> Caiet in loc. Aq. Lom. in <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>30.</hi> huc potius incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t enim quod amor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici eſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventior et ideo non incongrùe putatur melior <hi>1.</hi> Cum enim Deus ſit men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura totius per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis, ille actus qui nos deo ſimiliores red lit, reddit etiam perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiores, ac proinde ipſe eſt perfectior; cum nobilior actus formalis, non niſi a forma nobiliori oriatur doct. citat. ib. Ad hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c modum diſputant. <hi>2. Tis the naturall kindneſſe of man, to love his friend: but tis the heavenly kindneſſe of God to love our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. At the moſt</hi> virtus coram hominibus eſt, adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarios tolerare, ſed virtus coram deo eſt diligere. Ideo Paulus cum dixiſſet Charitas patiens eſt <hi>(1 Cor. 13.4.)</hi> continue adiunxit, benigna eſt. Ne fi patientiam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio non ſequatur, in deteriorem culpam odij virtus oſtenſa vertatur. Greg. M. Cur. paſt. part. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> admonit. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> is of a contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, &amp;c. That the love of our friends, that is, ſuch as have a naturall or morall relation unto us, is the more perfect Act. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch are the more perfect object, as being nearer united unto God by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19741:15"/> goodneſſe (amongſt the wicked there is no amity but<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 83.3.4.5.</note> conſpiracy) and to us by good turnes, namely by actuall conjunction; whereas our enemies<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 139.21.</note> (which muſt be none but Gods foes) are onely in poſſibility to be conjoyned unto either,<note n="h" place="margin">Inimicos dei perfecto odio o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe (ut odit eos David. <hi>Pſ. 139.22.</hi>) eſt quod facti ſunt diligere, &amp; quod faciune increpare Gre. Cur. paſto. part. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitione <hi>23.</hi> &amp; vid. Aqui. <hi>2.2.</hi> queſt. <hi>25.</hi> art. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; q. <hi>76.</hi> art. <hi>1 who teaches that no perſonall hatred is lawfull, unleſſe of thoſe who by revelation are known to be the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible enemies of God, and his Church, and ſo as well S. Paul in the New Teſtament, 2 Tim. 4 14. as David in the Old Teſtament, Pſal. 139.22. hates and curſes ſuch.</hi>
               </note> and ſo to bee loved of either. Againe the hatred of thoſe, whom nature, or vertue hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to us, is a greater fault, than the hatred of our enemies; therefore the love of them, is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vertue. 2. Laſtly, if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19741:16"/> the love of our enemies ſurpaſſe the love of our friends, why doth it not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo exceede the love of our ſelves, which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of that other love? And for the reaſons of the firſt opinion, they are more ſpecious than ſolid, and therefore perhaps the Doctor balkes them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deciſion. For firſt, by our Saviours Doctrine, the morall law forbids all private externall revenge, againſt civill enemies, or legall, and all inward hatred, even of thoſe whom they were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to kill, only what was abſtruſe in the Law, or obſcured by the Doctor of the Law, was in this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19741:16"/> caſe cleared, and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our Saviour in the Goſpel. Secondly, the love of our enemies is the imitation of the divine goodneſſe; and tis in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt difficult, but yet ſince<note n="i" place="margin">Difficultas non efficat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum in entita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e praſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem cum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo non ſit bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſed potius malum morale impedicas, ſc. actiones virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, licet ex ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidente prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat adjuvet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</note> difficulty infuſeth no moral goodnes into an act, tis not in a matter moſt worthy to be imitated. For doubtleſſe in God accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to our underſtanding (although in God as hee is in himſelfe all things bee the chiefeſt) his love of himſelfe and his love of his children, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before his love of his enemies, in our choiſe and method of imitation, inſtructing us, firſt here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to love our ſelves, then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19741:17"/> our<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum de caeteris paribus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectior actio; ſed praeſtantius eſt obiectum amicus quam inimicus, ergo. Mend <hi>2.</hi> Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um enim amici ideò eſt pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in ſuo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gravius quia privat ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum meliori virtute ſen actu. id. ib.</hi> 3. E. g. luc. 9.54, 55. For this cauſe our Saviour ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the Diſciples (ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies) for calling for fire from heaven upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans, ſaying, yee know not of what ſpirit yeare, intimating that ſuch furious malice becomes not the Miniſters of the Goſpel, but rather the ſpirit of meekeneſſe and gentleneſſe, which he taught by his owne example, Luk. 19.42. and cap. 22.51. and cap. 23.24. the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paul commends, 2 Cor. 13.10 2 Tim. 2.25 what Elias did (whoſe example 2 Kings 1.9. they pretended) was by extraordinary inſtinct and not of private revenge, but in zeale to Gods glory. In the New Teſtiment we reade onely of two ſo deſtroyed, Act. 5.</note> friends, then our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Divine love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins at home, and then it walkes neare home, but it ſtayes not there. Her line like the Sunnes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.3. goes out through all the earth, and her words (and workes alſo) unto the end of the world. And as the Sunne ſhee ſhines on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19741:17"/> bad and good. The good, whether neare or a farre of, in blood or Religion, ſhee loves in a ſubordinate reſpect unto the ſupreme good, for that either ſpirituall or morall goodneſſe ſake which is in them, for ſo our Saviour<note n="l" place="margin">Mark 10.21, 22.</note> loved the young man, which yet departed from him. The wicked and morally evill men, ſhee can love for the reliques of that naturall or created good which are in them, to wit<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 1.26, 27.</note> the Image of God which is not quite obliterated in the bodies, or in the ſoules even of wicked men, which are ſtill the ſame creatures they were, for eſſence, &amp; natural
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19741:18"/> properties and characters: yea charity could it finde no good in men, can make ſome, whilſt ſhee ſuppoſes and deſires God to effect it; ſhe loves them, as thoſe that may be good by Gods grace, as they be poſſible members of Ieſus Chriſt, though now appearing members of Sathan.<note place="margin">The breadth of Charity.</note> See then I beſeech you <hi>par la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo Charitatis &amp; mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, charitas omnia comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur, amicum colligit in deum, &amp; inimicum propter deum, unam Reimpublicam terram facit.</hi> Charity is of equall extent with the whole world, ſhe embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the univerſe in the armes of her affection, (imitating our Saviours
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19741:18"/> ſtretching out his armes upon the croſſe to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace both Iew and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile) ſhee gathers together her friends unto God, and her enemies for Gods ſake. Shee makes S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Aug in <hi>1.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Ioh tract. <hi>10.</hi> Beatus eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> domine, qui te amat, &amp; ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum in te, &amp;c. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te. Auguſt.</note> his bleſſed man, who loves God, and his friend in God, and his foe for Gods ſake. Shee (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Fathers judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) makes that excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding broad commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of whoſe perfection there is no ſuch end, as of other precepts. I have ſeene an end of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.96. But thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is exceeding broad, <hi>quia ubi eſt charitas, ibi non eſt Anguſtia,</hi> for where
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19741:19"/> for where there is Charity there is no ſtraitneſſe. S. <hi>Paul</hi> a man of tranſcendent Charity tells his <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that his<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.11, 12.</note> mouth was open towards them, &amp; his heart enlarged. Yee are not (ſayes he) ſtraightned in us (whoſe love is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant to doe you good) but yee are ſtraitned in your owne bowells: you want affection to receive, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſuch good<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>vis non Anguſtari? In lato habita,</hi> i. e. <hi>in Charitate.</hi> Wilt not thou then bee ſtraitned on what ſide ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, either in communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting good where it is due, or ſuffering evill which thou haſt not deſerved,<note n="r" place="margin">Dilatamini &amp; vos, ſc. haritate ib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>13.</note> dwell at large, that is, in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19741:19"/> Charity.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 101.2</note> In the midſt of this houſe thou ſhalt bee ſure to walke with <hi>David</hi> with a perfect heart, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Charity no perfection, for it fulfills the law.<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 100. Lat. Tranſlat.</note> 
               <hi>Arcta omnis malitia eſt, ſola inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia lata eſt.</hi> Malice and all wickedneſſe ſtraitens and ſhackells the ſoule, onely innocence, which is the immediate fruit of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is of a diffuſive<note n="v" place="margin">Out of the abundance of the Charity of the heart, the mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the words of Charity that tend to edification. And alwaies the heart is larger than the mouth, that affects more than this can utter. Sincere Charity ſpeakes more than ſhee talkes, yea ſhee cryes to God for others, with Moſes, Exod. 14.15. when her tongue is ſilent. But on the other ſide, the tongue may ſpeake many things for neceſſity, for vain glory, for advantag ſake, and yet all that is ſaid, may be nothing without charity 1 Cor. 13 1. Goe firſt get a charitable heart, then <hi>loquere ut te videam,</hi> ſpeake that I may ſee thy charity.</note> and enlarging nature. It wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens the narrow heart of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19741:20"/> man, into a receptacle for him who is incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, into a pleaſant walke, or holy Temple, for him whom the heaven of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens cannot containe. For God hath promiſed to thoſe that keepe his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes (which love fulfills) to walke amongſt them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.3.12. <hi>i. e.</hi> to dwell in them, &amp; to walk in them as in a Temple, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. But froward thoughts ſeparate from God: and into a malicious ſoule wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wilt not enter, ſayes the Author of the booke of Wiſedome, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.3.4. But to conclude this point, note, that though Charity reach unto all in the latitude of her exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19741:20"/> yet ſhee affects not all men in the ſame degree of intenſion. But as heat diffuſed through a large roome from the ſame fire, is more intenſe to thoſe that ſtand neare unto that fire, more remiſſe to thoſe that are farther of, but yet it warmes all more or leſſe: ſo Charity is extended to every one in the whole circuit of the world, but not <hi>equaliter</hi> equally: the heate of her affection is greateſt to the neareſt; ſhee teaches us as well to love one as another. For our neighbour is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other beſides our ſelves: but ſhee bindes us not, to love one as well as another, <hi>ordinavit in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19741:21"/> me Charitatem,</hi> ſaith the Spouſe,<note n="w" place="margin">Vul. Tranſ.</note> 
               <hi>Canticles</hi> 1.4.10. Hee hath ordered my charity.<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſian col.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. The degrees of Charity.</note> 
               <hi>Haec eſt charitas ordinata, odio habens nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quoſdam meritoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> jure plus diligens.</hi> This is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered charity, which hates none, but loves ſome more than others, for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts ſake. Love muſt bee without diſſimulation to all, not without ſeverall degrees to divers objects.<note n="y" place="margin">Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter plus cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis deo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus quam nobis. Nam Deum propter ſc, nos vero, &amp; proximos, propter deum diligere debemus. Auguſt. Lib. <hi>8.</hi> de trim, cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> The extremity or utmoſt of our love, is due to God: nothing is to bee loved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with him, all things in ſubordination to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19741:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> him.<note n="z" place="margin">Ille iuſtè &amp; ſanctè vivit, qui rerum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teger aeſtimator eſt. Ipſe est au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habet, ne aut diligat quod non eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum, aut non diligat quod eſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, aut amplius dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat quod mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, aut aequè diligat, quod vel minus vel amplius eſt diligendum, aut minus vel amplius diligat, quod aeque est di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igindum Aug Lib <hi>1.</hi> de doct. Chriſt. cap. <hi>27.</hi> Id. Aug ib. cap. <hi>23.</hi> in enumeratione obiectorum quae ſunt diligenda ordinem dilectionis inſinuat. <hi>1.</hi> quod ſupra nos <hi>2.</hi> quod nos <hi>3.</hi> quod iuxta nos <hi>4.</hi> quod infra nos ut not ex eo Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>29.</hi> Lit. A.</note> Next to him and under him, the Church challenges the height of love: Firſt, as ſhee is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, then as ſhee is Nationall, laſtly as ſhee is<note n="a" place="bottom">I meane limited to a particular dioces, or pariſh wherein wee live.</note> locall. This love men owe as Chriſtians. Now as the lives, of men are ſubject to the government of one kind or other, in reſpect not onely of religion but externall policy and order, they owe (as I ſuppoſe) love,<note n="b" place="bottom">
                  <hi>So</hi> Lucan <hi>ſayes of</hi> Cato, Lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>42. that he was</hi> Iuſtitiae cultor, rigidi ſervator ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſti, <hi>that his opinion was,</hi> Non ſibi ſed toti geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſe credere mundo, <hi>and therefore he himſelfe was,</hi> In commune bonus urbi pater eſt, urbique maritus.</note> firſt to mankind, to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19741:22"/> the good of the univerſe, then to that<note n="c" place="margin">Et Clcero ait, non nobis ſolum naſci mur, &amp;c. ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſane nobis pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo naſcimur, ſed patriae.</note> ſtate and commonwealth under w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they live. Laſtly, to that incorporation or place wherein they dwell. For ſtill (<hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> all things being alike) <hi>bonum, quò communius eo melius.</hi> Good is ſo much the more amiable, by how much it is the more generall. This love moves inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate creatures, to leave their particular nature, to ſerve the univerſall, as the ayre to deſcend to avoyd vacuity, which nature ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres. This love mooved <hi>Codrus,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Decij,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themſelves to death for their countries ſake. Is this a ſmall matter, to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19741:22"/> ſave a body politick by the temporall deſtruction, or abſciſion of one of the members? See the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of humane Charity,<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 32.31.</note> in <hi>Moſes</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 9 1.</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up their ſoules (in<note n="f" place="margin">Hom. 16. upon the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and bodies to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, to procure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſalvation unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple glory to God:<note n="g" place="margin">Coment in Lo.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſuppoſes thoſe wiſhes to have proceeded out of raſhneſſe and confuſion of mind, as if (ſaith he) they had bin in a ecſtacy, &amp; beſides themſelves, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that which was impoſſible, who may both returne that anſwer for themſelves, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19741:23"/> S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe gives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his boaſting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in the ſecond Epiſtle, 5. Chap. 13, 14. If wee bee beſides our ſelves, it is to God (to his glory,) or if we be ſober, it is for your cauſe (who are the Church of God) for the love of Chriſt conſtraineth us: The love of Chriſt, who ſo loved the Church that he laid downe his life for her, compells us, to deſire (if it may ſtand with Gods good will) to promote Gods honour, which is to ſhew plenteous redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by his rejecting of us and receiving of an whole nation into our place of favour. Though I may ſay
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19741:23"/> of the matter and effect of this wiſh, as<note n="h" place="margin">Vincentias Fill. Mor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> To. <hi>2.</hi> Tract. <hi>27. 2</hi> Qu. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fillincius</hi> ſpeakes of the alteration of the Lords day to ſome other. <hi>Hoc practice eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibile, abſolute verò poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile.</hi> This is a thing in its owne nature poſſible, abſtracted from all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and reaſons in the particular inſtance, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hinder the event, that one man ſhould periſh in the roome of many.<note n="i" place="margin">Melius eſt ut pereat unus quam unitas Bernard. Epi. <hi>102.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vnum pro multis dabitur caput.</hi> But becauſe we ſuppoſe in this caſe, God to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed the contrary to their ſeparation from him, &amp; we know them, being meere men, to have bin no ſitting mediatours for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ranſome of others, we
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19741:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> determine the caſe it ſelfe to be practically impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But did not Chriſt himſelfe, conditionally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of God,<note n="k" place="margin">Matth. 26.39.</note> a thing which was made by his Fathers determinate coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell impoſſible? So might <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> conuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſire, what could not be granted.<note n="l" place="margin">Opertet pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatis utilitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus publicas, mortalibus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternas antefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Caius Plin Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt <hi>18.</hi> Vnde Clau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dianus de ſuo Imperatore ait Nunquam publica privatis ceſſerunt commoda cauſis, And Lucan. loc. cit. <hi>ſaies that</hi> Cato's <hi>Heroicall diſpoſition, was</hi> Naturamque ſequi, patriaque impendere vitam. <hi>But as</hi> Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius <hi>ſayes of one,</hi> Hic homo verſus facit, &amp; tota ſibi fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a eſt. <hi>So ſome men ſtudying onely their owne ends, are as it were, a whole common wealth unto themſelves; contrary unto</hi> Cato, <hi>of whom the Poet addes further,</hi> Nulloſque Catonis inactus ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſit, partemque tulit ſibi nata voluptas.</note> But to follow the ſteps of Charity, by which ſhee deſcends, as it were by <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, from heaven unto the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19741:24"/> earth,<note place="margin">The degrees of private charity</note> and from God to man. You have ſeene her affection to community: Amongſt private objects, ſhee makes every man to himſelfe the firſt, the next is the wife, then the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, which are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred in honour before the other, not in love, in this reſpect they are left behind, that ſhee may be cheriſhed,<note n="m" place="margin">Ephe. 5.25.</note> which is fleſh of our fleſh &amp; bone of our bone: now we muſt love all others as our ſelves, none before our ſelves. Then followes in the order of nature, our Children &amp; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are our ſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and multiplied, our very domeſtique ſtate, and petty Common wealth:
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19741:25"/> not to governe, and nouriſh, argues more notorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Charity, then is uſually found amongſt<note n="n" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells: Next to our dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique family,<note n="o" place="margin">De modo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vivendi ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>5.</hi> cit. A Lombard. <hi>3.</hi> ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. <hi>29.</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. apud quem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de plura de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine diligendi.</note> S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> puts the houſhold of faith, <hi>quia ſanctior eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium copula, quàm corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Becauſe ſpirituall kindred is nearer than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall. But immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſucceede thoſe, whom canſanguinity, or neare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance adde unto us: Then come thoſe whom morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unites to our affections; our loving friends, thoſe that dwell neare unto us, our ordinary acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, our country men, ſtrangers, whom common humanity reſpects. In the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19741:25"/> laſt ranke, to our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charity are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, even our enemies;<note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 5.44.</note> whom not onely morall Philoſophers, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Scribes and Phariſes permitted men to hate,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 43. <hi>&amp;</hi> 47.</note> and proſecute with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. This is the order (in my opinion ſubmitted to better judgements) which we muſt follow in the diſtribution of our charity, with the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed caution <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> and in ſingle relations. Elſe plurality or increaſe of the fore mentioned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects alters this rule. <hi>e.g.</hi> wee muſt preferre one of our kindred naturall and ſpirituall both before one of the houſhold of faith,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19741:26"/> which is not of our Tribe: againe we may prefer god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrangers, before wicked kinſmen, or a loving kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man before a rebellious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible ſonne. So S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Loc. cit.</note> 
               <hi>plus debemus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere extraneos, qui nobis conjuncti ſunt vinculo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis Chriſti, quam propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quos qui deum non diligunt.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Hinc. Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſ. d. <hi>29.</hi> lit. F. obſervat. quod jubemur diligere deum ex totâ virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. <hi>i. e.</hi> maxime: proximum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſicut nos ipſos, non ſicut deum: Inimicos ſimpliciter, ſine addito. Quia ſi eos diligamus, et ſi minus quam alios proximos, ſufficit, &amp; S. Ambroſ. (cit. a Lomb <hi>3.</hi> ſ. d. <hi>29.</hi> Lit. c.) ſuper illud Cant ordinavit in me charitatem ait. <hi>1.</hi> deus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendus <hi>2.</hi> parentes, inde filij, poſt domeſtici: qui ſi boni fuerint malis filijs praeponendi ſunt.</note> But all other things being alike, this is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the naturalneſſe and ſincerity of love, as the Apoſtle phraſeth it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8. For ſo S. <hi>Pauls</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19741:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> runnes, Let them learne, firſt to ſhew kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or pitty, at home<note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſc.</hi> to themſelves, and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Then, as wee have opportunity let us doe good unto all men, <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to them of the houſhold of faith, Galath.</hi> 6.10. doe good to all, note here, that all mankind is the <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequate</hi> object of Charity to our neighbours. For with S. <hi>Paul</hi> all men are our neighbours. But the eſpeciall object of this Charity, <hi>is the houſhold of faith,</hi> that is, not any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſect, which chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the monopoly of the profeſſion of faith, but<note n="u" place="margin">Domeſticos ſidei, <hi>i. e.</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos Aug. comment. in Loc.</note> all Chriſtians in generall, which are indeede, as well
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19741:27"/> as title: For otherwiſe,<note n="w" place="margin">Salvian de Gub. dei l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Reatus impij, pium nomen,</hi> this name is their guilt, not their priviledge. And ſo conſequently, the more faithfull and holy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans men are, the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Love are due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. For we love our neighbour becauſe hee beares the Image and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription of the King of heaven. Therefore wee muſt chiefly love thoſe, who chiefly participate of that Image, ſuch are thoſe which endeavour<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 11.44, 45. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.16.</note> to be holy as God is holy. Theſe are of the houſhold of faith, heere of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. that is, by faith gathered into the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church which is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19741:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> the houſe of God. Now tis but equity that wee ſhould preferre Gods do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtiques before Forray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and ſtrangers, as they are<note n="y" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. <hi>ib. ſci.</hi> 19.</note> called before Aliens from the Common wealth of <hi>Iſrael, v.</hi> 12.<note n="z" place="margin">Eſtius in loc. Galat. <hi>6.10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ordo charitatis, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm quem (caeteris paribus) fideles infidelibus ſunt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendi, Additantem, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Otherwiſe an Infidell, or wicked man, in extreame neceſſity as to be relieved by our Charity, before one of the houſhould of faith, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary want.</note> This is S. <hi>Pauls</hi> order in Charity (in caſes alike) to preferre the faithfull, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the Miniſters, which are the Inſtruments to beget faith, by the word (towards whom hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites the <hi>Galatians</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>v.</hi> 6.) before thoſe that are not of Chriſtian faith or life. To all S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19741:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo allowes ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of charity, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he cals love to the faithfull; a great meaſure of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2 Pat. 1.7.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he calls brotherly kindneſſe: and our Saviour ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers this ſpirituall brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or kindnes before the naturall, that he ſeemes not to acknowledge this with the other,<note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 12.49.</note> leaſt it ſhould but ſeeme to ſtand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with it:<note place="margin">No parity of love in impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</note> but even in this houſhold of faith, alſo Chriſts own example con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes a parity in Love; of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I may ſay (as I think of the Preſbyterian parity what<note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi> lib <hi>9.</hi> Diſcrimina ordinum, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodias, quae ſi permiſta ſint, nihil eſt, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> in a caſe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik, once wrot. <hi>Nihil eſt hâc aequalitate in aequalius.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more unequall than ſuch equality: Affection
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19741:28"/> may put difference, for ought I know to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, without any inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: &amp; diverſity of merit, doth give juſt cauſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of degrees in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Chriſt himſelfe had one Diſciple beloved<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 13.23. c. 18.15. c. 20.22. c. 21.20.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that was S. <hi>Iohn</hi> who names not himſelfe,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nomen ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um celavit</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes, <hi>ne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anis gloriae cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſâ diligi ſe a Chriſto dicere videretur. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. Alex. in Ioh. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>S. Chryſ.</hi> alſo obſerves upon Ioh. 18.15. &amp; 20.3. that the Evangeliſt, not onely conceales his name in both places, but alſo puts Peters name before the periphraſis of himſelfe, becauſe he relates in each place the matter of his owne praiſe, in following of our Saviour with Peter to the judgement Hell, when all others had forſaken him, and in ſeeking his Maſter in the grave, and not finding him, there the Text ſaith, he beleeved, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Hee firſt had faith in the reſurrection of Chriſt, even before Peter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Now Salomon would not have a man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelfe, Prov. 27.2. And <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaies excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 8. <hi>Quod magnifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um referente alio fuiſſet, ipſo qui geſſerat recenſente vaneſcit.</hi> This ſerves well for our inſtruction againſt vaine glory, yet ſometimes for the illuſtration of Gods glory, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en men of the Holy Ghoſt (as <hi>Moſes, Paul,</hi> &amp;c.) have commended themſelves without arrogancy.</note> leaſt he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld ſeeme out
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19741:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> of vaine glory to boaſt of his Maſters affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him, or of his affection to his Maſter. Much leſſe can there bee any equality in our Love to all men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributively taken. Wee Love our ſelves, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of our ſelves; but wee Love not every part, ſuperiour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, noble and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile alike, but<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor, 12.25.</note> our more abundant honour, ſhewes our more abundant love to one before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And wee muſt love our neighbours onely <hi>as</hi> our ſelves, not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, not more: yea <hi>as</hi> much <hi>as</hi> our ſelves. This <hi>ſicut as,</hi> is a note of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19741:29"/> not of equality. Tis like <hi>as, as</hi> truly, <hi>as</hi> ſincerely; not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>as, i. e.</hi> in the ſame ardency of affection. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude ariſes from qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, not from quantity; the ſame diſpoſition of minde is required, not the ſame meaſure of love: our love to our neighbour, muſt bee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied out of our Love to our ſelves, as its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall; but it muſt bee written in a ſmaller print, though it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame matter, which conſiſts in theſe following rules! Our love to our ſelves, is true and unfaigned, for tis naturall, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19741:30"/> all hypocriſie is artificiall; let love to our neighbour alſo be without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.9. Goe not in with diſſemblers,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 26.4.</note> as it were to viſit thy neighbour in Love, ſaying with <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> art thou in health my brother,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ita qua tegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur nocet. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſa perdunt odia vindictae locum Sen. in Traged. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deae.</hi> Hence was learned that helliſh policy of the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> in <hi>Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardine,</hi> who deviſed how to kill his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies body and ſoule with one ſtabbe.</note> to betray him with thy mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heart, according to that of <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 26.24. Imitate not <hi>the ſleight of men, and cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, whereby they lye in waite to deceive, Ephe.</hi> 4.14. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaking, or following the truth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.18.</note> or being ſincere in Love; let us grow up in all things (which follow true Charity) into him, which is the head even
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19741:30"/> Chriſt. 2. Wee love our ſelves with inflamed and vehement affections. Let us alſo above all things, have fervent Charity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. Cold Charity is as great a ſolaeciſme in mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as cold fire in nature. 3. Our Love to our ſelves is a diligent and carefull Love, which cauſes every man to nouriſh and cheriſh his owne fleſh, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.29. thinking it not enough to abſtaine from doing any injury or violence unto it. And when any inevitable miſchiefe falls out, he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for remedy with teares of ſorrow, and if hee obteyne it hee rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth. Goe then and doe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19741:31"/> likewiſe to thy neighbour, even as thou deſireſt thy neighbour ſhould doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Bee yee all of one minde, having compaſsion one of another, Love as brethren, bee pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, be courteous,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Conſider one another to provok unto</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>love (mutuall) and to good workes,</hi> (the effect of true Charity) and her ſtrongeſt teſtimony.<note n="l" place="margin">Greg. M. in Ezech. lib. <hi>2</hi> Hom. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Amorem noſtrum erga proximum, plus bona ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio loquitur quam lingua,</hi> our Charity is better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the language of our hands than tongues. If ſhee be ſpeechleſſe in deeds, wee may toll the bell for her; ſhee is dying, and faith is departing with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19741:31"/> her; for <hi>faith without works is dead, Iam.</hi> 2.26. <hi>And faith workes by love, Gal.</hi> 5.6. ſuch workes you may finde in the next Chapter, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. they are of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all compaſſion and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo love fulfills the royall Law, the Law of Chriſt. See a Catalogue of Charities good workes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Tis the leaſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhee hath to thinke no hurt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. and to worke no ill, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. or tis a figurative com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, intimating that ſhee endeavours in all things to procure her neighbours welfare, and if any unexcepted ill bee happened unto him, her heart wiſhes, her tongue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19741:32"/> prayes, her hand labours for helpe; for the want whereof ſhee can mourne in ſecret, for the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with her in the<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 15.9.</note> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſhee calls her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours together, and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth without the bounds of a private breaſt. 4. Our Love to our ſelves is free, not mercenary, tis onely for our owne ſakes, not for any collaterall reſpect whatſoever. So love thy neighbour for his owne ſake, for his benefit, not thine: Such ſordid affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is but like bird-lime, cleaving to thy neighbour, to inſnare him to thy owne will, or like Ivy which by twyning about the Tree drawes out the vitall moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19741:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> This is to love thy ſelfe in thy neighbour, not to love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. This is the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Charity of the world, but tis enmity to God. 5. Our Love to our ſelves, which is the patterne of our love to our neighbour, is a pure, naturall, lawfull love, not that<note n="n" place="margin">Talis ſui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio melius o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium vocatur Auguſt. de doct. Chriſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.23.</hi> v. Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. d. <hi>28</hi> lit. A.</note> ſelfe-love iſſuing from originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which is a viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affection, whereby a man loveth in himſelfe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which is evill, or that which is good in an arrogant manner, which is indeede ſelfe-hatred.<note n="o" place="margin">Vulg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanſ.</note> For hee that ſinneth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his owne ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.5. So we muſt love our neighbours, not with a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19741:33"/> inclination, becauſe he is to thee as <hi>Levi</hi> was to <hi>Simeon,</hi> a brother in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, with whom thou haſt enjoyed, and doſt ſtill follow pleaſures, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of ſinne. How can this be good will, which worketh evill to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? but love him <hi>recta me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> with a right affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for ſome goodneſſe that is already in him, or which thou mayſt bee a meanes, by Gods helpe to work in him. 6. Selfe-love is very tender of our credits, a very favourable judge of our owne errours or faults.<note n="1" place="margin">Solet facun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſſe laetitia, &amp; Anguſtias clauſi pectoris aspernata geſtire Aur. Symmach lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>13.</hi> Cedant gaudia diviſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctis. Latius gaudet, qui &amp; alterius bonis paſcitur Id. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>24.</hi> Gaudia quibus pauci fruuntur auguſta ſunt Id lib. <hi>9.</hi> Spiſt. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> If we truely
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19741:33"/> love our neighbour as our ſelves, wee will not bee prodigall of his good<note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 22.1.</note> name, which is pretious to him, nor<note n="2" place="margin">The courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from this love are <hi>viſcata et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours but ſnares, not gifts, but baites, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a little is laid out, to make a gaine of it, as men powre downe ſome water to pumpe up more. <hi>De his vide Martialem lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep</hi> 56. <hi>lib</hi> 5. <hi>Ep</hi> 18. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Ep.</hi> 63. <hi>lib</hi> 7. <hi>Ep.</hi> 85. <hi>Plin. lib</hi> 9. <hi>Ep.</hi> 30.</note> rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>decenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of his actions, nor<note n="3" place="margin">Improbum eſt in alieno libro ingenioſum eſſe. Mart. in praefat lib. <hi>1.</hi> Engram. Nemo (ait <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lid:) Epigrammata mea ſcribat. Et nemo dicta mea loquatur, ne malè loquendo ſua facias. Non malè quod recitas incipit eſſe tuum. ut Id. Hiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiao ait.</note> perverſe interpreters of his words.<note n="q" place="bottom">Tacit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Facilius de odio creditur.</hi> Hatred doth willingly not know the beſt, and eaſily beleeves the worſt, <hi>quia irati ita vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="bottom">Iam. 3.17.</note> The wiſedome that is from above (to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate our Charity) is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19741:34"/> full of mercy and good fruits <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, without partiallity, <hi>ſc.</hi> to our ſelves, or without wrangling, <hi>ſc.</hi> about others errours, or whatſoever affaires: or laſtly without judging, as tis in the Geneva Bible:<note n="ſ" place="margin">And in the margent of our owne Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> And ſo conſequently without hypocriſy. So runnes the note there (which they I am affraid, have ſlipt over, who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve others too much) without examining of things with extreame ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as hypocrites, who onely juſtifie themſelves, and condemne all others, when in cenſuring &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning others, they are li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the ancient Moraliſts,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19741:34"/> eloquent againſt their own vices, and<note n="t" place="margin">Pompeius oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultior non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior. ſc. Mario Syl. &amp;c. Tacit. Hiſt. lib. <hi>1</hi> pag. <hi>473.</hi>
               </note> puniſh thoſe faults more ſeverely, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> themſelves follow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more cloſely, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe eagerly, as if their anger were rather out of envie then zeale,<note n="u" place="margin">C Plin. lib. <hi>8.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vir bonus verò ita alijs ignoſcit, tanquam ipſe quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiè peccet, ita ipſe a peccatis abſtinet, tanquam nemini ignoſcat,</hi> A good man is ſo ready to pardon others faults, as if he were an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall ſinner: Hee ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaines from ſinne, as if he would ſpare no offender whatſoever, but would be like<note n="w" place="margin">Lib. Ancab. pag. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rufus in Tacitus, cò immitior, quia toleraverat, ſci. diſciplinam virtutis. i. e.</hi> as ſtrict to others as to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19741:35"/> himſelfe. 7. Laſtly our love to our ſelves is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and perpetuall, as being naturall. For <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra non dilaſſatur opere.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture herſelfe is not weary with action, onely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments ſhee uſes faile at length. But Love it ſelfe is an inward affection, to ſhew the externall effects whereof onely the body is required. No marvaile then, that Love never failes,<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 13. ult.</note> even then when it cannot appeare without, <hi>ſed</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Greg. in Ezech. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Hom. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>deo occulta amoris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciunt Greg.</hi> But our hidden Love is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the ſearcher of the hearts, <hi>cum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non poſſumus, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum volumus operari Ib.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19741:35"/>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Auguſtus cum eſſet lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uriae ſerviens, erat tamen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſdem vitij ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſſimus ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Aurelius vict. in vita Auguſti. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerrimus fidei exactor eſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidus, mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a perſequitur periurus, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vitia in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis habemus, noſtra in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go. Senec. de ira lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi> Faciet nos moderatiores reſpectus noſtri ſi conſulueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; nos, nanquid ſic peccavimus. Id. ibid Aut ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n poſtea ſortè peccaturi ſimus humana fragilitate? ſic Apostolus moret Galat. <hi>6, 7</hi> &amp; vide Tit <hi>3.2, 3.</hi>
               </note> Let our love to our neighbour alſo bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and never degenerate into hatred. <hi>No man ever yet hated his owne fleſh, Eph.</hi> 5.29.<note n="a" place="bottom">Caſſiodorus tract. de amec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut ignis, non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt non ardere, ſic Charitas non poteſt non amarc.</hi> As fire never ceaſes to burne, ſo Charity never ceaſes to Love:<note n="b" place="bottom">Auguſtinus ad Iulianum comitem.</note> 
               <hi>Charitas quae deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poteſt nunquam vera fuit. ſc. ſed ficta, ſeu fictilis.</hi> Charity which can ceaſe, was never true,<note n="c" place="bottom">Sc. veritate permanentiae, ſi forte vera fuit veritate eſſentiae,</note> but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, or brittle.<note n="d" place="bottom">As a glaſſe which ſhines and makes a faire ſhew for a while, <hi>ſed dum ſp endet, frangitur,</hi> but is bone broken, when it gliſters moſt.</note> Abide in my Love ſayes Chriſt,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19741:36"/> 
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.9. And as it is there in the vulgar Latine, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nete in Charitate,</hi> Abide in Charity, let brotherly love continue:<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>And let us not be weary in well doing</hi> (which is the fruit of Charity) <hi>for in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wee ſhall reape if wee faint not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What it is to fulfill the Law and how Love fulfills the Law.</note> You ſee what it is to love our neighbours as our ſelves. Now to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the Law, that is, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all the precepts of the Law, in that manner which, the Law requires. As hee is ſaid to fulfill a mans will, who executes all the contents thereof. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her's the difference, mans will may be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the utmoſt by man, but Gods Law is fulfilled
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19741:36"/> onely <hi>quoad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of imperfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, if ſincere: not <hi>quoad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the rigour of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſo that men may live without all ſinne (as the<note n="f" place="margin">Pelagianor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dogma ſuit <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ut docet Hier. in dial cont. Pel. Script.</note> 
               <hi>Pelagians</hi> conceited) and come to the height, or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on ultra</hi> of Charity, as afterwards<note n="g" place="margin">Haereſis fuit Begardorum et Beguinarum, in concilio Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennenſi Anno Dom. <hi>1311.</hi> (cum novem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijs corum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farijs dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus) damnata, poſſe homines in hac vita, ad tantum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionem Charitatis pervenire, ut reddantur penitus inpeccabiles, &amp; amplius (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Anto. hist. part. <hi>2.</hi> Tit. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> § <hi>2</hi>) In gratia Charitatis proſicere non valeant.</note> others imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. There is a double perfection; one of parts, which wee call integrity, another of degrees, which we call abſolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, Pſal.</hi> 19.17. <hi>ſc.</hi> not onely eſſentially, but in all reſpects. And ſo is love abſolutely perfect in it
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19741:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19741:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19741:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19741:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19741:39"/> ſelfe, and relatively to us, as it points out to us the way of perfection, the Law of God. But wee in this life are not perfect in love, but onely in perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of parts: in degrees, our love muſt ſtill increaſe and abound, <hi>Phil</hi> 1.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15. till wee all come into a perfect man, <hi>ib. v.</hi> 13. which is, when this mortallity hath put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, then we ſhall fulfill the Law of Love (as the Saints now doe) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any defect at all, when wee ſhall know as wee are knowne.<note n="h" place="margin">Ex parte di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligimus quia ex parte cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcimus Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. d. <hi>27.</hi> l. F.</note> Here we know but in part, and therefore can love but in part. With <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> we may &amp; muſt have reſpect to all Gods
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19741:39"/> Commandements but with him, in the laſt verſe of that <hi>Pſalme,</hi> wee have our faylings: For<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 19.12. Iam. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>who can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand his errours!</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Non dicimus hominem poſſe omnis peccati expertem eſſe: non timemus tamen aſſerere, poſſe hominem per gratiam le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem implere, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eâ impletione vitam aeternam promereri Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm.</note> 
               <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> himſelfe dares not averre, that any man can live without all manner of ſinne, but onely without mortall ſinne; yet he feares not to maintaine, (out of this Text and the like) that a man aſſiſted by the grace of God (<note n="†" place="margin">Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum enim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doctos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat (iudice Voſſio lib. <hi>6.</hi> hiſt. Pelag.) an Pelagius ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noverit aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gratiam inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, quâ exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuvemur ad opera pietatis, utcunque, in hoc differunt quod generalem gratiam agnoſcant Papiſtae, quam nec docuit, nec novit unquam Pelagius.</note> wherein they ſeeme to differ from the <hi>Pelagians</hi>) may fullfill the Law of God: So that by ſuch fulfilling of the Law, they may merit eternall life. But ſince that ſinne indefinitely taken, is the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19741:40"/> tranſgreſſion of the Law,<note n="m" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.4.</note> and they that tranſgreſſe the Law, cannot fulfill it exactly, <hi>ſecundum totum perfectionale,</hi> but <hi>integrale,</hi> according to intenſive, or graduall, but onely exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and integrall perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Since, if love fulfill the Law by grace,<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 11.6.</note> there can be no reward of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: yea, ſince we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme no love, but onely what we owe (as our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes)<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> we cannot hire it out for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of ſalvation. Alas wee have not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to pay our debts, wee ſhall ſtill owe love when wee have payed abundance of love, and doe wee thinke with the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19741:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Inſtar viduae <hi>2.</hi> King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>4.</hi> erat Synagoga (Iudaica) ſine ſponſo Chriſto, cui libellum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudij dederat prior maritus <hi>Iſa. 50.1.</hi> pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererat, quia lex gratiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre non vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat (ideò eius rudimenta in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firma vocat Paulus &amp; ege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Galat. 4.9.</hi>) nec poterat Adami debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perſolve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, Nec ſibi ſuaque animae providere. Habebat autem vaſa com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modata, quia legem uſque ad Christum commo latam habebat, venit autem Chriſtus, &amp; ex lechytho cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſui oleum ſanguinis effudit, &amp; adimple vit vaſa vacua ſc. legem <hi>Matth 5.17.</hi> Ex eo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo &amp; ſatisfacere pro originali &amp; actuali peccato poſſumus, &amp; vivere de reliquo deo grati &amp; accepti. Sebaſt. Gomeſius in <hi>Pſal. 50.16. We may indeede live acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and pray with David in faith Pſalme 19. verſe the laſt. But wee cannot live a meritorious life to our God.</hi>
               </note> Widdow, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. by a miracle of grace, to obtaine ſuch a plenty, that wee ſhall have enough to pay, what dues wee owe to God and man, and then to live upon the reſt and purchaſe alſo with it? Let us rather take our Saviours advice, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. when yee ſhall have done all thoſe things that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you, ſay wee are unprofitable ſervants, we have done that which was
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19741:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> our duty to doe; wee are but ſervants, therefore our obedience is our duty. We are unprofitable ſervants: our obedience is but of ſmall value in it ſelfe, and to our maſter no way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our obedience is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="q" place="margin">Quare ergo datur praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſi impleri nequit? Reſp. Quia non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte curritur, ſi quò currendum eſt, neſciatur, Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſ. d. <hi>27.</hi> lit. G.</note> perfect nor merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, our<note n="r" place="margin">Omnis noſtra perfectio eſt imperfecta Bernard. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas in quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam eſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta, in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam imperfecta, perfectiſſima verò in hâc vita habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non poteſt ut Aug. ad Hieron. loquitur.</note> perfection is actually imperfect, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate onely in deſire and preparation of minde, and in ſincere endeavour, by which wee labour to bee<note n="ſ" place="margin">Matth. 5.48.</note> perfect as our heavenly Father is perfect. The beſt are but like the Image of <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Dan. 2.32, 33.</note> their feete are of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19741:41"/> clay, made of fraile earth, which cauſes them often to walke on weakely, ſometimes to fall dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, although their heads bee of gold, <hi>i. e.</hi> though their firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and reſolutions, bee pure and ſincere, towards all the wayes of God; which yet God calls and in favour accounts the<note n="u" place="margin">Ezek. 36.27.</note> fulfilling of the Law. But to conclude this point, our Apoſtle meanes that love fulfills the Law, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus, according to the ſincere deſirs of the heart; <hi>aut quoad praeparationem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi;</hi> or elſe according to perfection of parts, and uprightneſſe of minde; and that in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19741:42"/> 
               <hi>conjuncto</hi> as we have ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occaſions of doing good, not all at once, as if every act of Love were the ſumme of the Law. As tis evident by his enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of parts, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſome of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Commandements:<note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 13.9.</note> yet out of the order af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet them downe<note n="x" place="margin">Saint Paul there quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; puts the ſeaventh before the ſixt, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford matter for ſome idle Criticke to worke upon, but for us tis enough to know that our Apoſtles ſcope was not to rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but onely to give the abridgement of them.</note> (perhaps to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that they are all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to love, which knowes no firſt nor laſt, amongſt them) with a forme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the parts not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not <hi>dubitative,</hi> but <hi>incluſive,</hi> and if there bee any other Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſignifying that love
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19741:42"/> is as<note n="y" place="margin">Militum non eſt interpretari iuſſa ſed exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui Tac. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is obſequij gloria ſufficit. Id.</note> ready to obey, as God to command, leaving all authority to God, <hi>ſibi obſequij gloriam relinquens,</hi> leaving onely to it ſelfe the prayſe of obedience. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this concluſive ſentence is alſo excluſive (love ſo fulfills the Law,<note place="margin">Without love no fulfilling of the Law.</note> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out love the Law cannot be fulfilled) for he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends in one, that is, in this one precept of Charity, offends in all, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10. <hi>quia violat vinculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> as breaking the band of the whole Law, ſaies S. <hi>Aug. lib. de verâ &amp; falſâ penitentia cap.</hi> 14. <hi>(ſi fortê is liber ſit Auguſtini.)</hi> For the concluſion it ſelfe, though the rigour of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke ſuffer mee not to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19741:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> prove it, yet I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one or two parallell places of Scripture for the illuſtration thereof, and a ſentence or two of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers agreeable thereunto. The firſt and chiefeſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 22.40.</note> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounder and fulfiller of the Law that ever was, Chriſt Ieſus, who informes us that on theſe two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (<hi>ſc.</hi> of the love of God, &amp; our neighbour) hangs all the Law and the Prophets.<note place="margin">Galat. 3.14.</note> Then let S. <hi>Paul</hi> here witnes to himſelfe (&amp; no doubt but his witnes ſhal be true. All the Law (ſaith he) is fulfilled in one word that <hi>verbum abbreviatum</hi> in S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> opinion) thou ſhalt love thy neighbour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19741:43"/> as thy ſelfe, which precept <hi>Moſes</hi> gives, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.18. This love explicitely ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fills the ſecond Table, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely alſo the firſt. For thou canſt not love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, unleſſe thou love thy ſelfe firſt. Thou canſt not love thy ſelfe unleſſe thou love him that is thy <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> thy chiefeſt good, and <hi>intimius tibi quam tu tibi ipſi</hi> (as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayes of him) more intimate with thee than thou art with thine owne ſoule, in whom thou liveſt, and mooveſt, and haſt thy being. The love of God then abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely fulfills the whole Law,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.15.21.23. 1 Epi. Ioh. 3.17.</note> and is oft put for the whole ſervice of God:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19741:44"/> and the love of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour fulfills halfe the Law, with reference to the love of God, owe nothing to any man but love, <hi>ſc.</hi> which payes all duties: but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here, as alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. (with our Saviour <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.) names onely the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſecond Table,<note n="i" place="margin">Cum duo praecepta ſint amor Dei, &amp; proximi pro u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troque ſaepe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m ponitur, Lom. <hi>3.</hi> ſ d. <hi>27.</hi> lit. h.</note> becauſe theſe are the moſt palpable &amp; manifeſt fruits of love, appearing to the example of men and glory of God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the ſeeming zealous obſervation of the firſt Table, in hearing and preaching of the Word and the like duties, men ſometimes deceive not onely others Charity, but their owne ſoules alſo, by
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19741:44"/> the art of ſeeming. Againe for that in caſe of urgent neceſſity, when the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all performance of both kinds of duties to God and man (which are alwayes beſt united) cannot bee done together, the firſt table yeelds to the ſecond. God will then have mercy and not ſacrifice,<note n="a" place="margin">And Chap. 12.7. and out of Hoſ. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.13. And hence wee may collect alſo, why love is magnified, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. verſe the laſt, even above faith that<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 13.46.</note> precious Iewell of the Goſpel, for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe whereof a man ought to ſell all that hee hath, as of himſelfe. So that even in the Goſpell, the love of God is called the greateſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19741:45"/> and the firſt, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> love of our neighbour is accounted, the ſecond like unto it <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.38, 39. 1 Becauſe faith in its owne nature abſtracted from the fruits and effects thereof, hath reference onely to God, and ſo pertaines to the firſt Table, but love hath relation both to God and man. 2 Becauſe faith in that abſtractive conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on lyes hidden in the heart, and ſo is knowne onely to God: but love is like fire in the boſome, which will breake out, and cannot be concealed from man. 3 Laſtly, for that love in its owne nature is a more noble and heroicall vertue than faith, and of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19741:45"/> infinitely longer duration, fulfilling the Law of God unto the end, and<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> being without all end, ſhining<note n="1" place="margin">Charitas in patriâ ſerven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior eſt quam in via. Aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num enim ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius diligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, adeptum, quam deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet Sanctus Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> doct. Chriſt. cap. <hi>38.</hi> vid. &amp;c. <hi>39.</hi> Eſt Ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tas in hac vita, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens, profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, perfecta (ſc. ſuo modo) perfectiſſma vero eſt in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Vt aſſerit. Lomb l. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e diſt. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> moſt bright in heaven as the Sun without a Cloud: and whilſt that faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues with it tis as it were<note n="d" place="margin">Iam 2.26.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> if not the life, yet the breath of it. For faith without workes is dead, and faith workes by love. Onely in a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive conſideration, as faith is the inſtrument of our juſtification, and ſo the chiefe meanes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, faith is of more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency than love, which is onely an evidence and teſtimony of faith.</p>
            <p>For the Fathers, if you pleaſe to recollect in your
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19741:46"/> mindes what I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy noted out of S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I ſhall have no neede to bee tedious in heaping up new teſtimonies, onely heare S. <hi>Hierome</hi> againe deſcribing the vertue of divine love, putting forth the utmoſt of its ability in the ſervice of God, not onely doing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, but not daring to doe any thing which hee doth not require.<note n="z" place="margin">Hier. Epiſt. ad Caelant.</note> 
               <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vim obtinet vera di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio, &amp; totam ſibi amantis vendicat voluntatem. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil eſt imperioſius charitate. Si vere Chriſtum diligimus, nihil magis velle, nihil om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino debemus agere, quam quod illum velle cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:19741:46"/> And Saint <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Hom. <hi>27.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Evang.</note> ſayes, <hi>omne mandatum de ſola dilectione eſt &amp; omnia vnum praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſunt, quia quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid praecipitur, in ſolâ Charitate ſolidatur,</hi> All the precepts are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one: for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the foundation of them all. <hi>Charitas est multiplex lex. dei,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Vulgar.</note> 
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.6.<note n="c" place="margin">Id. Greg. Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>10</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> vid &amp; ib. c <hi>6 7.8.</hi> Et ſi placet. vid Aug. l. <hi>1.</hi> de doct. Chriſ. c. <hi>35.</hi> vbi docet quod Amor dei eſt ſumma Scripturae.</note> 
               <hi>quae a duobus praeceptis incipit, &amp; mentem ad innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera pietatis opera (de queis Apostolus,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.) <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiformiter accendit;</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the manifold Law of God, which begins from two precepts, to wit, the Love of God, and the Love of man) and diverſly excites the minde to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mumerable
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19741:47"/> workes of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſummes up (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.) in ſundry particulars. The generall wayes according to which love fulfills the Law, are three, of which in the next place.</p>
            <p>Love fulfills the Law three wayes, as <hi>Voſsius</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ger. Voſſ. hiſt. Pelag. l. <hi>3.</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> theſ. <hi>3</hi> pag. <hi>360.</hi>
               </note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently diſtinguiſhes, and out of him, word for word almoſt our <hi>Weemſe?</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Weemſe</hi> of the 3 Lawes 1. <hi>tom pag.</hi> 45.</note> and I ſhall informe you out of both, adding di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers illuſtrations &amp; proofes for your farther inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The tearmes of the diſtinctions are 1. <hi>Effecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vè, i. e.</hi> effectively. 2. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductivê, i. e.</hi> reductively. 3. <hi>Formaliter, i. e.</hi> formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is, briefly as the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19741:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> principall, as the end, as the forme of every law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Love fulfills the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Law effectively as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principle, or impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive cauſe of every legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate action. Love is the onely incitation, and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to true and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience. Firſt (ſaith <hi>Moſes) Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God:</hi> Then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>and keepe his charge and his statutes, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 11.1. <hi>And yee that love the Lord</hi> (ſayes <hi>David) hate evill, Pſal.</hi> 97.10. For himſelfe he reſolves thus, <hi>I will delight my ſelfe in thy Commandements which I have loved, Pſal.</hi> 119.47. In the next verſe he addes,<note place="margin">Vid. ib. v. <hi>167</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19741:48"/> 
               <hi>my hands alſo will I lift up unto thy Commandements which I have loved:</hi> See loves vertue, iſſuing from the heart to the hand, from affection to operation. And therefore perhaps the Law is ſayd to have gone forth out of Gods hands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.2.<note n="f" place="margin">Coment. in loc.</note> that it might come into our hands. <hi>Oleaſter</hi> ſuppoſes the precepts of God to bee called the workes of God,<note n="g" place="margin">Eſa. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>quia ideo praecipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut eaòperemur:</hi> Becauſe they are therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that we may not onely intentionally and verbally but actually ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill them, which is done by love. <hi>Quodlibet agens propter amorem agit, quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19741:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> agit Aquin.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>qu.</hi> 28. <hi>art.</hi> 6.</note> Every agent workes for ſome good, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the love of that good cauſeth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m to worke. The worldlings caſt-away carnall love upon ſeeming good. Godly men place ſpirituall love, upon ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good: The love of Chriſt conſtraineth us ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Amor meus, pondus meum, illo feror quocunque feror,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Aug. Confeſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> my love is the weight which poyſes mee in the wayes of God, ſo that I bee not carryed away as it were with the winde of every Novell doctrine, or with every worldly vanity. Common reaſon informes
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19741:49"/> us in this, that men doe not obey, or ſerve thoſe whom they hate, I meane, that their mindes are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſervants to ſuch though their bodies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may bee their enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſlaves. Serve yee one another by love ſayes our Apoſtle, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.13. But <hi>Non exterquebis amari,</hi> Love is not extorted by violence, but invited firſt by love it ſelfe. Love is the Whetſtone of love: So God himſelfe invites our love to him, by commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his love firſt to us, by his<note n="k" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.9, 10.</note> Sonne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. that our faith in the Sonne<note n="l" place="margin">Galat. 5.6.</note> may worke by love, towards God againe.<note n="m" place="margin">Charitas ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix eſt, ex qua omnes pullu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant virtutes Auguſt. lib de gratia Chriſti cap. <hi>18.</hi> vid. &amp; cap. <hi>20.</hi> ib.</note> Hence the whole office
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19741:49"/> of Chriſtianity alſo is compriſed in this one word, Love, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>v. ult.</hi> So love fulfills not onely the morall Law, but with all the Law of faith, as the Apoſtle phraſeth it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. So that <hi>ſine Amore, fides eſſe poteſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe non poteſt</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Aug de Trin. lib. <hi>25.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi> Similiter lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Bapt. cap. <hi>8.</hi> &amp; ib. lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> without love faith may be, but it cannot profit. But by love faith workes,<note n="o" place="margin">Charitas, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſt omnium cuſtoſque vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum <hi>Greg.</hi> Curio paſt. part <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> admonit. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and keepes all manner of Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which follow Love, as the leſſer wheeles are moved by the greater. Hence it is that S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the piety of the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> the worke of Faith, and the labour of love, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. And our
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19741:50"/> Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.40. ſayes, that the whole Law, hangs upon the two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of Love, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating perhaps, that love is as it were the hinges of the Law, upon which it is turned too and fro, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace good, and avoid evill. Chriſt teacheth us alſo, that there is no true Love without keeping Gods Commandements, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.15.21.23. and no true keeping of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements without love, verſe the 24. <hi>ib.</hi> The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Diſciple repeates the ſame doctrine, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.3. and Ch. 3.17. 2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6. verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Love fulfills the Law reductively, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19741:50"/> every lawfull opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is reduced to Love, as to its end, for which it was performed; and in this ſence it is an externall cauſe, and moves morally, as comprehended <hi>ſub noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one boni,</hi> as good: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, as an efficient cauſe, it moves phiſically, as it is a naturall quality and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. That love is the end of the Law,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches us, <hi>The end of the Commandement is Charity, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> the end why God gave his Law to us, is, that we ſhould love him, &amp; our neighbour. So love unites all the precepts into one Commandement, in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine. <hi>Finis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepti, dilectio gemina, Dei
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19741:51"/> &amp; proximi, praecurrat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio dei, caetera in illum confluant, ut dilectio tui, &amp; proximi Aug.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> The end of the precept is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble love, of God, and of our neighbour: Let the love of God have the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency, and all other love followe after, as of our<note n="r" place="margin">Qui ſe prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe diligit, non ſe veſert ad deum, ſed ad ſeipſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus, non ad incommuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile aliquid (cui toto af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu inharen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum) conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur Aug. de doct. Christ. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> ſelves and others: wee ought to love God for his owne ſake, our neighbour, and all Gods creatures, for Gods ſake;<note n="ſ" place="bottom">Amor fruendi quibuſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que creaturis, ſine amore creatoris non eſt a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o: per amorem creatoris, bene quiſque utitur etiam creaturis Aug. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cont. Iulian. cap. <hi>3.</hi> Si teipſum propter teip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, non debes diligere, non ſuccenſeat alius homo, ſi etiam ipſum propter deum diligis Aug. loc. cit. de doct. Chriſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> and to performe our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall duties to God and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19741:51"/> man, not of conſtraint, or for filthy lucre, but onely for loves ſake. Love is like the <hi>Indian</hi> Figge-tree, of which <hi>Scaliger</hi> writes<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exerci.</hi> 166.</note> that ſhee having ſhoote up her branches a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient height, reflects them downe againe, to take new rooting in the earth, and ſo makes a kinde of naturall arbour. Gods love is the firſt ſeede which cauſes our love to take roote, and to fructifie: (For Charity growes not like the fruit of the earth in the golden age, without any ſeede ſowne, I meane without the ſeede of Gods grace ſowne in the heart, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:19741:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Conterraneus noſter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en: Beda in libro quem ſcripſit contra Iulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum Eclane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem (qui hodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eque praefatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis loco, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarijs eius ſuper Cantica praefigitur) te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatur Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus nativam qualitatem, quamque gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nunquam gignit, ſed quandoque nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trit, &amp; auget. Charitas (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum eos) velut flax eſt, quae ſuâ ſponte ardet, ſed ſpiritu, quaſi vento agitata, vehementius inflammatur. Sed abſolutè ſecundum Apoſtolum. Fructus ſpiritus Charitas <hi>Gal. 5.22.</hi>
               </note> imagined. Then Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the aſſiſtance of Gods grace, ſhootes up her branches a good height, even to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and from him ſhee reflects them downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine unto the ground, (to wit) to the men of the earth, and takes new roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there. So <hi>Greg. Mag. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Mora. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Per a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem Dei amor proximi gignitur: Per amore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, amor Dei g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itur. Nam qui amare Deum neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligit, profecto diligere prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imum neſcit.</hi> Tis the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles phraſe, to ſhew Loves
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19741:52"/> firmeneſſe, &amp; fruitfulneſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yee being rooted and grounded in Charity. This fruitfull roote ſtrengthens the whole body of Religion, and ſends forth the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold branches of piety, bearing conſtantly the fruits of good workes, and not onely the faire leaves of good words. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour you know curſed the Fig-tree, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> made a faire ſhew at a diſtance, &amp; yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no fruit, when he came neere unto it, although the time of fruite were not come. To teach us to bee alwayes fruitfull in the good deeds of Charity, becauſe God allowes no
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19741:53"/> ſeaſon of ſpirituall barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no not in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of old age, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.14.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Charity ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fills the Law formally, <hi>quia finis in moralibus, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet rationem formae, i. e.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in morallity, the end hath the Nature of a forme alſo. Charity is as it were the ſtampe, in the which every lawfull action is to be coyned, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which how reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſoever, tis but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14. Let all your things be done, in, or with Charity. All things done without Charity are as it were nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19741:53"/> Hence Charity is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. the band of perfection, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.14. becauſe it u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites and couples all good duties together, which faith workes by love, and ſo may be called in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <hi>ſides formata:</hi> A faith that hath her right forme; but faith not working by love is a dead faith, and ſo <hi>ſides informis,</hi> a formeles faith, as ſome of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines doe juſtly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. See Biſhop <hi>Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in his booke of the Covenant of Grace, page 229, 230. who will not yeeld to <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that love is the inward conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutive forme, and ſoule as it were of faith, yet denies
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19741:54"/> not that it is the morall or conſequtive forme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Then know that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you performe the Commandements of God materially, or according to the ſubſtance, as <hi>Iehu</hi> fulfilled the will of God, in deſtroying the houſe of <hi>Ahab:</hi> yet if you doe them not formally in Charity: <hi>i. e.</hi> principally in love to God, ſecondari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to your neighbour, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the Church of God, you may pull on your heads vengeance, as <hi>Iehu</hi> did (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4.) in ſtead of a bleſſing. God preferres adverbs before ſubſtantives, hee doth not ſo much regard what is done, as in what manner:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19741:54"/> the manner ſpecificates the action, and makes it good, or bad morally. Laſtly, note (to conclude this point and therewith the whole explication of the Text) our actions may bee formed by Charity, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly and explicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is, when in the act it ſelfe wee thinke of the love of God, and of our neighbour, to forme the act thereby, as wee goe to Church, out of our preſent love to the houſe and ordinances of God; we goe to viſit our neighbour in any diſtreſſe, becauſe wee ſuppoſe it a duty of love ſo to doe: or ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implicitely and virtual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when the love of God
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19741:55"/> and man is habitually ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in our hearts, but yet we doe not thinke thereof, in ſuch or ſuch an action. I conceive, that for the maine duties of godlineſſe, actuall love is neceſſary, but habituall love ſufficeth for thoſe which are of leſſe moment, and more ordinary. Whatſoever we doe S. <hi>Paul</hi> will have us doe it to the glory of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. and ſo conſequently out of our love to God. But in ſome things, as the habituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of his glory, ſo the habituall love of him, as it is a ſufficient motive, ſo a ſufficient forme of our actions. The love which I have propoſed unto you,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19741:55"/> is not a meere notion, but a reall vertue, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in ſpeculation but action, not in knowledge but application. The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects unto which love is to bee applyed are foure in generall, although in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars <hi>infinite</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Ang. de doct. Chriſt l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>unu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ſupranos,</hi> the firſt and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt is above us, to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before our ſelves, or any<note n="x" place="margin">Si deus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni homine am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quiſque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet eum dilige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quam ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Aug. de doct. Christ. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> man whatſoever. <hi>Alterum quod nos ſumus.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">As the love of wife, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, children kindred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors, friends, &amp;c. Hence <hi>Lomb.</hi> obſerves 3 <hi>ſent. d.</hi> 29. <hi>lit. C.</hi> that the Commandement concerning our parents is <hi>honora,</hi> honour, not <hi>dilige,</hi> love, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we doe that naturally.</note> In the next place our ſelves: <hi>Tertium quod juxta nos eſt.</hi> Thirdly, he that is next our ſelves, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>Quartum quod infra nos eſt.</hi> Fourthly, that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19741:56"/> which is below us, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. There are no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>)<note n="z" place="margin">Ib. cap. eod. &amp; cap. <hi>26.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concuſſa natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra lege quod ſumus, &amp; quod infra nos eſt, diligimus, quae lex etiam in beſtias promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata eſt.</note> concerning the ſecond and fourth object of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: For wee naturally affect them, and they who love not God, or their neighbour, love yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their owne fleſh even as bruit beaſts alſo doe by nature. <hi>Fugax enim animus ab incommuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li lumine omnium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore, id agit ut ipſe ſibi reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, &amp; corpori ſuo: Et ideo non poteſt niſi &amp; ſe &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſuum diligere:</hi> For the minde that flyes from God the unchangeable light, and ruler of all men, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours it ſelfe to domineere with the luſts of the fleſh.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19741:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> Therefore it can love one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſelfe, and the fleſh. Selfe-love then and ſo all ſecond love which flowes from that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, hath no neede of any<note n="a" place="margin">That is, any eſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of love, as <hi>Lomb.</hi> againe notes <hi>Ib. diſt.</hi> 28. <hi>lit. A. p.</hi> 144.</note> precept, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently requires no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, being like the<note n="b" place="margin">Auguſti d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum fuit apud Senec. in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. Epitom. controverſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> page <hi>286.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius noſter ſufflaminan dua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt a Deo non currere, ſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur. ſc. in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Declamator in Seneca, qui ſufflamine potius indigeat, quam irritamento,</hi> rather to be reſtrained and held in, than to bee incited and thruſt forward. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of love then, and ſo the neceſſary motives thereunto, are onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God above us, and our neighbour next unto us. But becauſe our love to God, and to our neighbour, is but
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19741:57"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eadem eſt Charitas, Dei &amp; proximi, ſed quia aliud eſt deus, &amp; aliud proximus, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina dicitur, vel propter du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>os motus, qui in mente ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur. Ideòque &amp; duo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta dicuntur, ut alterum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, alterum minus, quia mens magis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga deum, quam proximum, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur Id. ibid. diſt. <hi>27.</hi> lit. C.</note> one love, according to the Schooles, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe tryes our love to him, by the love of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.9, 10. cap. 3.14.17. cap. 4.8.12.20, 21. &amp;c. <hi>Nec deus, ſine proximo, nec proximus ſine deo, diligi poteſt:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>27.</hi> lit. H.</note> Neither can God bee loved without our neighbour, nor our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour without God. For how can he that loves God contemne him that is Gods Image, and whom God commands to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? And whoſoever loves his neighbour as he ought. <hi>Quid in eo diligit niſi deum?</hi> what doth hee love in him, but God? Hence the love of our neighbour<note n="e" place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Gal. 5 24</note> is put for the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19741:57"/> whole Law. <hi>Quò magis enim, a dei dilectione rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, eò &amp; a proximi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more diſtamus, quanto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piùs, dei amori adhaeremus, tanto &amp; proximi: quantò &amp; proximi, tantò &amp; dei. Dorotheus doct.</hi> 6. Even as in a genealogie the nearer men are in the collaterall lines, to the firſt roote, or common head of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, the nearer they are of kinne, the one to the other: and <hi>e converſo</hi> the nearer they are of kinne the one to the other, the nearer they are ſet to the Father of their Tribe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The words were written by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus,</hi> but are authoriſed by S. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 17.28.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19741:58"/> we are all Gods off-ſpring, God is the Father of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the nearer we draw unto God in goodneſſe, the nearer we muſt needes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to one another in good will; and the nearer we draw to one another in love, the nearer wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach even to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:<note n="f" place="margin">Velut lineae quo magis a ſe invicem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, eo magis a centro remo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſunt, &amp; e converſo, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> magis a centro eò magis a ſe invicem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Deus vero (ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm Empedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis doctrinam) ſphaer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius contrum eſt ubique, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferentia vero nuſquam. Et Iumblichus testatur deum circuli ſymbolo hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicè pingi ab Egiptiis. In circulo hoc infinito nos lineae ſumus, Deus ipſe centrum eſt noſtrum. Caetera Dorotheus loco citato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pro nobis applicet ſc. Deo per charitatem proximi accedimus, per odium ab eo quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum a proximo recedimus.</note> And the farther we are from our neighbour in affection, the farther wee are from God in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and the more wee depart from God by an evill heart, the more wee ſeparate our ſelves from
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19741:58"/> our neighbour by a maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart.<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> The whole current therefore of my remaining diſcourſe and time, ſhall run to drive men to that love of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture moſt ſtrives againſt, turning all Charity aſide as it were into a private channell of ſelfe-love, which (like the ſea) ſhould diſperſe her ſelfe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 5.16. Let thy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines be diſperſed abroad and rivers of waters in the ſtreetes. This is a note of <hi>Davids</hi> good man, that he hath diſperſed abroad, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.9. and is ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by<note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.9.</note> S. <hi>Paul:</hi> Now
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19741:59"/> becauſe Charity delights in order, give me leave to begin at home, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her to my ſelfe and my brethren of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Clerum</hi> to the Clergy.</note> that hence, as from the head, it may flow downe like <hi>Aarons</hi> ointment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. round about us, that others may run after the ſmel of it. My brethren ſuffer the word of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to a double kind of love, mutuall and paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. 1. To provoke you to mutuall love conſider I pray; firſt, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law God led his people by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Pſal.</hi> 77.20. by brethren, which had but one heart, and ſo but one hand as it were to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19741:59"/> conduct,<note place="margin">Of mutuall love amongſt the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</note> and feede Gods flocke. For theſe two are reckoned amongſt Gods Prieſts by <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.6. Howſoever tis evident that they were both Gods inſtruments to promulgate the Law. Secondly note, that under the Goſpel Chriſt calling his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, chuſes firſt one paire of brethren, <hi>ſc. Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew,</hi> then another, <hi>ſc. Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn, Matth.</hi> 4. Againe, when Chriſt ſent his Diſciples forth to preach, hee ſent them out by paires; the reaſon of which Commiſſion made thus to two and two is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the author of the imperfect worke upon S, <hi>Matthew, Homil.</hi> 7. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19741:60"/> the unity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of the Miniſters of the Goſpel was requiſite for the laying of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Chriſtian Churches; which muſt be layd in love, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the building, and the builders: For the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they muſt not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to the faith by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile violence, but rather are to be perſwaded unto it by love. They who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a trowell in one hand, and a ſword in the other, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4.17. uſed not that weapon to build the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but to offend their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. And as by love they are drawne to the faith; ſo by mutuall love they are faſtned and ſetled
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19741:60"/> in it.<note n="i" place="margin">Knit or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love. In the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall tis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. In the Epiſt. to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Coloſſ. 2.2.</note> Love is the very caement of the Temples walls, uniting them in the band of peace, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.3. Love is the very ſtrength of the ſpirituall building. Support you one another by love, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.2. on the contrary ſide: <hi>Non aedificatur altare ex ſectis lapidibus:</hi> the Altar muſt not be built of hewen ſtones, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.25. Hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſtones (ſaith <hi>Iſidore</hi> out of <hi>Origen</hi> the maſter of Allegories) are thoſe that cut unity aſunder, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves from Chriſtian ſociety, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or ſchiſme: Chriſt will (ſaith he) have none ſuch in his myſticall body, of which the Altar was a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19741:61"/> figure: but thoſe onely that are conſolidated in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of faith, and good life, are of his Church. But mutuall love is moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially required in reſpect of the builders of Gods houſe, or Altar. For the<note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 3.16. 1 Cor. 14.40. and v. 33.</note> diſcord of the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, cauſes a Babell, <hi>i. e.</hi> confuſion of all things, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of decency and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that is, a curſe for a bleſſing. Let mee adde, that as God choſe more brethren to preach the Goſpel, than to publiſh the law, ſo hee now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more abundant love from us towards one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In this reſpect alſo it may bee, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of love is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19741:61"/>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 13.34.</note> new, which is not abſolutely new, 2 <hi>Epiſt. Ioh. ver.</hi> 5. Becauſe Chriſts doctrine doth not onely commend Charity, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo inlargeth it, if not above the wideſt ſence of the Law, yet certainely farre beyond the practiſe of the Iewes, and the gloſſe of their doctours, as wee are taught, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.43. &amp;c. This is indeede to love one another, as Chriſt hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, with entire and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent affection. Above all things then let us have fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent charity amongſt our ſelves: Let us who are the Prieſts of God,<note n="m" place="margin">Levit. 6.12, 13.</note> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually nouriſh this fire of Charity, in the Temple of the Lord: Let it be infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19741:62"/> by the antiperiſtaſis of worldly hatred, that <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licidium charitatis</hi> (as<note n="n" place="margin">Thomas a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va villa in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione quadam.</note> one phraſeth it) that froſt of Charity in theſe latter dayes foretold by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.12. The love of many (even of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſhall wax cold; ſee the reaſon there alſo, becauſe iniquity abounds, the which whilſt we reprove, wee become the<note n="o" place="margin">1 Kings 22.8. and Gal. 4.16.</note> enemies of the whole world: yet I cannot conceale what is ſaid in the verſe before. Many falſe prophets ſhall ariſe &amp; ſhall deceive many: And therefore the love of many may well be abated towards ſuch, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſeeke every one their gaine out of their
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19741:62"/> quarter, but not of ſoules; theſe are worldly wiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede fooliſh prophets. But let us have ſalt in our ſelves, and peace with one another, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.50.<note n="p" place="margin">In quae verba, ſic ait Greg. M. Cur. Paſt. part. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> admonitione <hi>23.</hi> ſal (i. e. ſapientia) ſine pace (ſc. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis) non vittutis eſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſed dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia enim iſta eſt anima is, terrena, diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica: ſed ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia quae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurſum deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, primò eſt pudica (i. e. quae caſte intelligit) deindo pacifica, quia per elationem ſe minimè a proximo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſocietate diſjungit. Quo plus ſapiunt homines (ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiâ ſc. terrena quae inflat) eò a concordiae virtute deſipiſcunt: Haec Greg.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> the ſalt of ſpirituall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; that peace which Chriſtian Charity brings; which are two vertues happily conjoyned, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily ſevered: For the wiſedome that deſcends from above is firſt pure, (not earthly ſenſuall and corrupt) then peaceable (not proud and factious, <hi>i. e.</hi> deviliſh) <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.15.17. And the love that deſcends
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19741:63"/> from above is wiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete, not inordinate, and inconſiderate: It abounds in judgement, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9. Let both the gaine which wiſedome teacheth us, and the fellowſhip which cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity invites us unto, be, if not onely, yet eſpecially ſpirituall, let us not by the one be given to<note n="q" place="margin">Tit. 1.7. and 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, nor by the other to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy, know you not what one hath not onely ſpoken in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but publiſhed to the view of thoſe that<note n="r" place="margin">2 King. 18.26.</note> ſtand upon the wall? I am loath to repeate, what hee was bold to write, perhaps we may tranſlate it thus. <hi>Miniſtri omnium hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum incundiſsima ſocij,</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:19741:63"/>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Phraſis ipſa est Tiberij Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis, alias Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berij Neronis, qui cum nocte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, continuumque biduum, cum Pomponio Flac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eo &amp; L. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, epulando potando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumoſiſſet, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri Syriam Provinciam, alteri praefec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam urbis confeſtim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit, codicillis quoque Iucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimos &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium horarum amicos, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſus Suet. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quorum textus, est fictile peto plenum, &amp; quorum pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terium, est cantharus.</hi> The beſt way of confutation, is rot by retorting contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, which Charity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids, but (as the Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pher did refute him that diſputed againſt naturall motion, onely by walking) by ſpeaking the words<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 26.25.</note> and performing the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of truth and ſobriety. Elſe woe be unto thoſe by whom ſuch ſcandalls come againſt all the reſt. In the meane while, untill Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity teach men better lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, let us poſſeſſe our ſolves in patience, and comfort one another with theſe words, <hi>The Diſciple is not above his Maſter.</hi> Our
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19741:64"/> Maſter was accounted a glutton and a wine bibber, becauſe hee came eating and drinking, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.19. And the Baptiſt came neither eating nor drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they ſayd, he hath a Devill <hi>v.</hi> 18. So the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious cenſurer, with<note n="u" place="margin">1 Kings 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah,</hi> makes himſelfe hornes of iron to puſh on both ſides, and with him there, verſe 24. hee will be ſure to ſmite the Prophet, if not with the right hand of juſtice, yet with the left hand of calumny. As the Satyriſt ſayes, <hi>O Laer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiade, quicquid dicam aut erit, aut non.</hi> So in this caſe (it ſeemes) tis to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for the Prophet to take care what to ſay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:19741:64"/> doe: For O man of God, whatſoever thou ſpeakeſt or doeſt to the uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, either muſt be evil or not, if not, malice will make it ſo, if ſo already, cenſure ſhall augment it: malice ſees things as it were through the water, ſo that what is ſtraight ſeemes crooked, and what is ſmall ſeemes great, if it be bad enough to be ſeene at all. And cenſure (as I have inſtanced) like the winde, blowes with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall violence, upon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that are oppoſite the one to the other: And ſo it is to bee regarded as a winde that paſſeth away (in raſh breath) &amp; returnes not againe, as it were in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19741:65"/> judgment to conſult upon what is paſt, to apply <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> words<note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 78.39.</note> to another ſenſe then he intended with good leave: S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the judging men of <hi>Corinth</hi> plainely, I<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3, 4, 5.</note> paſſe not to be judged of you, &amp;c. where he furniſhes us with divers reaſons (which your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations may make uſe of) to defend our ſelves with, againſt humane judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or if you pleaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how our Saviour hath forwarned &amp; forear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us, in his Apoſtles, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.<note n="y" place="margin">v. 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> See what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands you to doe, to love one another, ſee how hee encourages you to ſuffer by his example. If the world hate you, you know
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19741:65"/> that it hated me before that it hated you, &amp;c. againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect what he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 13.35.</note> By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another: Charity is as it were the livery of Chriſtianity, but the eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cognizance of the miniſtery of the Goſpel, even an indelible character thereof. Had we now (as the Apoſtles once had) power to worke miracles, yet without this gift, that, and more than that, were <hi>totum nihil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> all nothing, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1.2.) I meane, no ſure ſigne of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. If a Lords ſervant or any officer goeth forth without the neceſſary badge of his ſervice, or
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19741:66"/> office; few or none per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will or can take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him, but if he have that with him, every where he is knowne by it. So Brethren, if we walke without Charity, who can tell whoſe miniſters wee are by other common ſignes? But Charity is<note n="z" place="margin">Sic ea verba Critici diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt ex Ariſt. <hi>1.</hi> Rhet. <hi>2. Of paſtorall love ¶ 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no common ſigne, but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per note, by which wee may manifeſt our ſelves to be Chriſts Miniſters. In the next place I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto your Charity the Church of God, firſt in generall,<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.28.</note> then in that particular reſpect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your duty is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially engaged univerſall care <hi>authoritative</hi> is
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19741:66"/>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Apoſtoli enim habebant pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem uni loco, aut certae ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, ſed pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariam, &amp; vniverſalem: Docete (ait Chriſtus) om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes gentes: Et pradicate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Creature Marc. <hi>16</hi> Sic Paulus miſſus eſt ad omnes gentes Act. <hi>9.15.</hi> Rom. <hi>1 5.</hi> ut not Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend. Epiſc. Sariſburienſis Comment. in Coloſſ. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi> At verò Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi cuiuſque authoritas, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricta eſt uni diocaeſi, aut uni ſaltem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciae, vel denique, uni Patriarchatui, nec ipſo Romano Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo excepto.</note> Apoſtolicall, generall is Epiſcopall: and no man takes this honour upon him but he that is called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. As was <hi>Aaron</hi> to the High-prieſt-hood as S. <hi>Paul</hi> inſtructs us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. But charitable care or carefull charity to deſire, and to our utmoſt power, to uphold the peace and proſperity of Hieruſalem, is the duty of each inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our paſtor. To intimate what cordiall love, they that miniſter at the Altar, eſpecially thoſe that weare the Ephod, ought to ſhew to the Church of God:<note n="c" place="bottom">Exod. 28.29.</note> the legall High-prieſt, when he went to miniſter
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19741:67"/> before the Lord, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to weare a Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of judgement upon his heart, upon which were engraven the names of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which may teach us to beare within our hearts, in a Breſtplate of righteouſneſſe the names (as it were) of all thoſe Tribes, and families which profeſſe the ſure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere foundation of the Chriſtian faith, by unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned prayer and endeavour for the common ſalvation of them all; why ſhould it not be in the myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it is in the naturall, where the heart wiſhes, the tongue prayes, the hand labours, for the good, not
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19741:67"/> onely of ſome parts, but of the whole compound? But let the name of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> amongſt other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of our peculiar people, amongſt the flocks of our companions, bee ſtamped in Capitall Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, even as a ſeale upon our hearts, as the chiefe object of our Charity, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the which we ought to longe, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> longed after all his, <hi>Philip. cap.</hi> 1.8. in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus, as having them in his heart, <hi>v.</hi> 7. Let us fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low S. <hi>Pauls</hi> example, by practiſing S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Take heede unto your ſelves, and unto all the flocke, &amp;c.</hi> This is to love the flocke of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19741:68"/> Chriſt by Chriſts owne inference, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. But let your love to the flocke of Chriſt bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Charity, which is an orderly and deſcreete af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not<note n="d" place="margin">Vſurpatur ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haec vox aliquando a patribus (fate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or) ſenſu opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ut ab Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Epiſt. ad Rom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, criticita men pro vicioſo amore accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a love not once named by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, a blinde, inordinate indulgence, or carnall love, ſuch as was in old <hi>Eli</hi> towards his ſonnes, or in Amnon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his ſiſter. A corrupt and corrupting love, which either gives, or ſuffers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill example, which the Scripture accounts the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of our ſelves, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If wee ſhall love the flocke of Chriſt, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 29.25</note> 
               <hi>Demetrius</hi> magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Diana's</hi> Image, becauſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19741:68"/> by that meanes wee have our wealth: we make Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity a ſordid trade, and defile our ſelves with fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre, and ſo in effect hate our ſelves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.5.<note n="f" place="margin">Vulg. Tran.</note> being enemies to the good of our owne ſoules. On the other ſide, if indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent love provoke us to flatter men, and forbid us to reproove them, we in Gods phraſe and account, hate them in our hearts, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. Wee are Gods Prieſts, wee muſt not mix with our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, either the hony of ſweete tongued flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for advantage ſake, nor the gall of bitter malice, for revenge ſake; but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſacrifice muſt be ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19741:69"/> with ſalt,<note n="g" place="margin">Levit. 2.13.</note> our ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice muſt alwayes be<note n="h" place="margin">Mark. 9.49. Ib. verſ. 50.</note> ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the fire of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table zeale to ſanctifie them, and with the ſalt<note n="i" place="margin">Coloſſ. 4.6.</note> of diſcretion, to give both our words and actions a good ſavour, ſometimes with the ſalt of ſeverity alſo, which though it cauſe corrupt mindes to ſmart for the preſent, yet it cleanſeth their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the end: This is to make our love to abound in judgement.<note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 1.9.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to ſeparate ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and love: Shall I come unto you with the rod, or in love<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.21.</note>? But S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Aug. cont. Epiſt Parmen. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> conjoynes them together in the hand as of a naturall, ſo of a ſpirituall
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19741:69"/> Father. <hi>Habet &amp; virga charitatem, Sed aliud eſt charitas ſeveritatis, aliud eſt charitas manſuetudinis. Aut una quidem charitas eſt ſed diverſa, in diverſis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur.</hi> The rod hath love with it: <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 23.4. Ib. verſ. 1.</note> found comfort not onely in the ſtaffe of Divine ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſo in the rod of Gods correction, who was his Father &amp; his She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheard, and therefore hee preſumed that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he did was for his good. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that when he comes he will not ſpare; yea, God himſelfe bids <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Iſaiah 58.1.</note> to lift up his voyce and ſpare not. Laſtly, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teaches us, that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19741:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>plures corrigit timor, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet amor meliores,</hi> the feare of the rod amends the moſt, though love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the beſt: yet that ſervile feare which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitts of no filiall love, and that rigid ſeverity, which ſhewes no fatherly love, ſeldome produce any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. The bowells of a Father muſt be ſeene (though obſcurely as the Sunne through a thinne Cloud) through the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry countenance of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Although offences have withheld &amp; covered the love of mildeneſſe, and let the offenders diſcerne the love of ſeverity, which is indeede the ſame love, but workes diverſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19741:70"/> divers objects. But ſome may reply to all this, that the forwardneſſe of our affection to our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had prevented this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, were they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent objects of our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall love, but too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are more like unto thoſe<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note> beaſts, with whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> fought at <hi>Epheſus</hi> than unto the flocke of Chriſt, whoſe properties are innocency, gentleneſſe, concord. But we with the Diſciples<note n="r" place="margin">Matt 10 16.</note> are ſent amongſt devouring Woolves. Our heritage is not fallen in a goodly place, <hi>Sed ubi licet culti ſint agri, inculti prorſus animi &amp; mores,</hi> Men with us manure their lands,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19741:71"/> they<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ier. 4.3.</note> breake not up the fallow ground of their heavy and ſtony hearts; ſo that wee are enforced to ſow the ſeede of the word amongſt thornes: with us, as with<note n="t" place="margin">Ezek. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> are briers &amp; thorns, which vex and fleece us, yea with him, wee dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Scorpions, which carry ſtings in their tailes, like thoſe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. <hi>ſc.</hi> to wound us with virulent detraction, and killing cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, although like thoſe Scorpions <hi>v.</hi> 7. they beare the faces of men, <hi>(id eſt)</hi> ſaith the Geneva gloſſe, they pretend great gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and love, but they are wiſe, politique, ſubtile. The truth is, wee paſtours
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19741:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> are to wicked worldlings, as ſhepheards to the<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 46.34.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> even an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now wee have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Hieronymus in Epiſt. qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam hanc ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominato au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore citat.</note> that <hi>Fruſtra laborare, nec aliud fatigando ſe, niſi odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quaerere, extremae eſt dementiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To labour in vaine and to get onely hatred for our love, is a point of extreame folly: <hi>Et plura ſaepe pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Objection"/> 
               <hi>dum demeremur, quam dum offendimus:</hi> there may bee more offence ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſuch unwelcome officious love, than at a juſt neglect or contempt.</p>
            <p>Well all this, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſwer"/> with griefe ſuppoſed at leaſt, to bee done and ſuffered, may not yet provoke us to caſt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19741:72"/> away our Chriſtian pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and charity. Firſt, for their hard-heartedneſſe &amp; ſtupidity, let it not be the occaſion of ſcorne, but pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which may the rather moove our Charity to ſhew<note n="x" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> meekenes towards them, to prove if God will at any time give them repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for their words, feare them not as God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in the forecited place; For their malice, or power to doe us wrong, Chriſt hath told us how farre they can goe, and forbids us to feare them alſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28.<note n="y" place="margin">Hicro. in Ep.</note> 
               <hi>Apud Chriſtianos enim non qui patitur, ſed qui facit contumeliam (vel injuriam) miſer eſt.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19741:72"/> Chriſtians not hee that ſuffers, but hee that doth any wrong, is a wretched man.</p>
            <p>From our Saviour wee learne not onely patience to overcome injuries, but Charity to forgive thoſe that doe them: <hi>Ille enim, poſt alapas, crucem, flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, blaſpemias, noviſsime pro crucifigentibus oravit: Pater ignoſce ijs neſciunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim quid faciunt:</hi> Chriſt after hee had ſuffered buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets, ſtripes, repoaches, yea and part of the cruell paines of that woodden racke the Croſſe, at laſt he<note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 23.34.</note> prayed for them that crucified him: <hi>Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, &amp;c.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.23. c. 3.16, 17. 18, &amp;c. For our imitation.</note> propoſeth Chriſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19741:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> his maſter. It is alſo in Chriſts perſon, and for our inſtruction what <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaias</hi> ſpeaketh, Chap. 49.4, 5. <hi>I have laboured in vaine, &amp;c.</hi> and Chap. 65.2, 3. <hi>All the day long have I ſtretched forth my hands to a rebellious &amp; gaineſaying people,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 10.21.</note> hee who was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Prophet, yea the Lord of life, who came himſelfe like<note n="c" place="margin">2 King. 4.</note> 
               <hi>El ſha</hi> to the dead child, to raiſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> from a ſpirituall death, when the<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 3.21.</note> Law (like the ſtaffe of <hi>Gehazi</hi>) could not give life, hee (I ſay) came unto his owne to teach them; (and did that ſeeme a ſmall matter?) Alſo to ſhed his blood for them, and his owne recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19741:73"/> him not, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.11. No marvaile then that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes his Diſciples to looke for no better enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement in their owne country, with men of this world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.57. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.44.</p>
            <p>If you will cull out of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, a man <hi>edecumatae charitatis,</hi> of the choyſeſt perfection of Charity. Behold S. <hi>Paul,</hi> proſecuting his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> with unwearied affection, though he well perceived that the more he loved, the leſſe he was beloved of them:<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15.</note> love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like an inheritance in Law, which either ſolely, or moſt uſually deſcends, not aſcends; ſo love flowes
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19741:74"/> more freely &amp; plenteouſly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God to mankind, than it can aſcend from man to God againe: For the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Divine bounty doe but in part and from few places, and that ſlowly too, returne to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence they came. In like manner Love deſcends very eaſily from parents to children, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any legall conſtraint, but it comes up ſo hardly from children to parents, that there is neede both of a precept, and<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.24.</note> promiſe to draw it forth. Now Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are ſpirituall Fathers, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe the onely<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.15.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and therefore hee beares
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19741:74"/> with them, as parents with their unruly children. And he puts all faults off with an elegant and pleaſant Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Wee are fooles for Chriſt his ſake, and you are wiſe in Chriſt: we are weak, and yee are ſtrong, yee are honourable and wee are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemes that ſome Schiſmatickes in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> had ſlighted S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as a<note n="i" place="margin">Secundum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teum traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ptulus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat tricubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis doctor, vir. ſci. puſillus, &amp; exig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: Non mirum ideo eſt, ſi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ille fuit e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onginquo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiae Mos enim eſi vulgi, ut imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res (iudicio Taciti lib pri. hiſto.) Ita quoſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitos, decore Corporis aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare: Sed quam parva ingentes arcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la condit opes.</note> man of deſpicable preſence though of powerfull elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in thoſe letters that he wrote unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. A tricke there is which Sectaries have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe daies; every way to magnifie their owne factioniſts, and to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19741:75"/> vilifie their ſuppoſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts, to cry up in the one, vocall impudence for zeale, and meere memory for learning, to cry downe in the other, holy feare and modeſty for lukewarme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ignorance: in the one to extoll the art of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, in the other to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee reall worth; affection either deluding or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaying judgement.</p>
            <p>But ſince yee<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.19.</note> ſuffer fooles <hi>Animalia gloriae &amp; aurae popularis mancipia,</hi> as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſtiles philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, <hi>i. e.</hi> vaineglorious Animals that enſlave themſelves to popular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, ſuffer me (alſo to ſpeake) or receive me as a foole ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. v. 16, 17, 18, 21.</note> and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19741:75"/> would to God you would beare with mee a little in in my folly, <hi>v.</hi> 7. that is, I pray you ſuffer mee to commend my ſelfe as fooles uſe to doe, though not fooliſhly with them, to beſpeake a good report from the people; but as<note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.5.11. Ch. 12, 13. Ch. 10.8.17, 18.</note> compelled by you to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie Gods gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in me, and ſo to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the author of all good. Thoſe men looke on things after the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Chriſt forbids all ſuch kind of judgement,<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 7.24.</note> But the kings daughter is all glorious within, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13. Laſtly, ſee how hee meetes with thoſe that reviled him, practizing
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19741:76"/> upon them that revenge which hee had learned of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44. and which hee taught his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> Chap. 12.20. &amp;c. <hi>ſc.</hi> by rendring good for evill, by powring upon their heads, who were within full of heart burning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him,<note n="o" place="margin">Carbones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregabis, &amp;c <hi>Rom. 12.20.</hi> Non in male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed in correctione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; poenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ut ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus beneficijs, ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octus fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vore Charita tis, inimi us ſſe deſiſtat Hier. circa finem lib. <hi>1.</hi> Adverſ. pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag.</note> onely ſuch coales as were kindled by the fire of Charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. hee ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> wee are buffeted, it followeth in the next verſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and wee labour. Againe there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reviled wee bleſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecuted wee ſuffer it, yea more yet, verſ. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> being defamed we intreat; <hi>ſc.</hi> God to forgive our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19741:76"/> and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. we labour and ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: ſaith he, <hi>Odimur &amp; laboramus, maledicimur, &amp; benedicimus,</hi> we labour and ſuffer reproach: wee bleſſe being reviled. Mee thinkes this is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>motto</hi> that can bee inſcribed on <hi>Levi</hi> his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, like that divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe on his forehead, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.36. and on his horſes bridles, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord:</hi> It is like the inſcription up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his enſigne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Croſſe of Chriſt: (A figure then terrible to the adverſaries onely, not to the profeſſours of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by this wee overcome, even the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19741:77"/> whole world: for faith is our victory, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.4. and that works by ſuch love as I have deſcribed: with w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I conclude all that I have hitherto ſpoken, and this almoſt in S. <hi>Paul</hi> his owne words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. I write not (I ſpeake not) theſe things to ſhame you (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Clergy or Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) but to warne you, (on that ſide as beloved breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, on this other) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſonnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="§" place="margin">2. Of the application <hi>ad populum:</hi> To the Laity.</note>Then in the next place, <hi>Levi</hi> having firſt received his charge (as once his maintenance apart from his brethren) be<note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 49.2.</note> ye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together all yee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonnes of Iſrael, in the unanimity of affection, in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19741:77"/> the unity of the ſpirit, and in the band of peace, and heare attentively what your ſpiritual Father ſaith, in his houſe &amp; in his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both old &amp; new, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning firſt generall love towards all men: Secondly ſpeciall love towards all Chriſtians: Thirdly, more particular love towards the Church, firſt Nationall, then Locall, wherein you live, and whereof you are members: Fourthly ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar love towards the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, but chiefly towards your owne ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſtors: Fiftly and laſtly, mutuall love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one another.</p>
            <p>In our Liturgie wee are truely taught to pray for<note n="*" place="margin">1, Of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards al men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:19741:78"/> all men; which we cannot doe as wee ought, if wee be not in charity with all, therefore we muſt love all: all men are our brethren, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>jure naturae,</hi> (as<note n="q" place="margin">Tertul. in Apolo. cap. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) <hi>i. e.</hi> by the right of nature, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth brethren to love one another. Againe (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſti lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi> Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homo, in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſt homo diligendus eſt propter deum, &amp;c.</note>) Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a ſinner, as a ſinner ought not to be beloved, yet<note n="ſ" place="margin">Charitas eſt dilectio qua d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur Deus propter ſe &amp; proximus (qui eſt omnis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo) propter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel in Deo. Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſen. diſt. <hi>27.</hi> lit. B concords cum definitione Auguſtini lib. <hi>3.</hi> de doct. Chriſ. Cap. <hi>10</hi> Sicut dilexi vos: id eſt, ad quod dilexi vos, ſci. ut f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſitis, ut vitam habeatis. Lomb. loc. cita. lit. D. &amp; ibid. lit. b, ait. ſicut dilexi vos id eſt: propter deum. Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> enim niſi deum, dilexit in nobis Chriſtus, non quem h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebamus, ſed ut haberemus? &amp;c. ex Aug. in loc. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> every man as a man is to bee loved for Gods ſake, <hi>i. e.</hi> as bearing the ſame image of God with
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:19741:78"/> us, or as a convertible unto God by our meanes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This is to love one another, as Chriſt hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. Namely to love for Gods ſake, and that wee may bee made our ſelves, and make others the ſonnes of God, that ſo they and wee may have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life together. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this love following our Saviours precept, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.45.48. is correſpondent to God his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> his love to mankinde. Verily God is loving to every man, and his mercy is over all his workes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.3. The mercy of man (of fraile imperfect man ſurely) is toward his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19741:79"/>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Sci. <hi>His neighbour by reaſon of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, or ſome benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall relation: whereas hee ſhould love his neighbour in the large<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> extenſion.</hi> i. e. <hi>every man:</hi> est enim proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus multiplex ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lomb. <hi>3.</hi> ſen dist. <hi>28. 1.</hi> conditione primae nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis. <hi>2.</hi> Spe converſionis; bis duo bus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, quiſque ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo eſt proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>3.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitate cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis, ſic eſt una tantum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milia proximorum. <hi>4.</hi> Ratione beneficij exhibitionit. <hi>5.</hi> Addendum ratione propinquae cohab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tationis quae eſt vulgaris potius quam theologica verbi acceptio. <hi>2. Of ſpirituall love towards al thoſe that hold the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of chriſtianity.</hi>
               </note> but the mercy of the Lord is upon all fleſh, ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach, Ecclus.</hi> 18.13. then ſince God his hand of bounty is ſtretched out, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all fleſh, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion of uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it, that ſo ſhrinkes up our armes, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold them out to our owne fleſh?</p>
            <p>But truly God is (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) loving, or good to <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 73.1. ſo let our chiefe love be towards the whole Church of God, ſtirring up our prayers, and all our endeavours for the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19741:79"/> generall peace of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> For they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper that love her, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6.</p>
            <p>Surely if every man bee to bee loved as a man (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath taught us) though not as a ſinner: much rather every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is to bee loved as a Chriſtian, though not as an erronious Chriſtian: As erronious onely I ſay. For if hee deſtroy the foundation, by any <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie as S. <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2.1.<note n="w" place="margin">Non enim quaelibet haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis deſtruit fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum &amp; mortifera eſt. Notiſſimum eſt quod tum apud patres, tum Scholaſticos; quilibet error circa religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ortus hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>citur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteratus vero &amp; pertinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter defenſus, ſchiſma voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Immo Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias papa, aſſerentes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes aliquas eſſe, haereſeos damnavit.</note> or if he apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatize from the faith, hee is then no Chriſtian at all.</p>
            <p>It was a famous proverbe in the primitive times
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:19741:80"/> which now reflects infamy upon our dayes:<note n="x" place="margin">Tertull. in Apol. ca. <hi>39.</hi> &amp; vide <hi>Act. 4.32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ecce ut ſe invicem diligunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani.</hi> See how the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians love one another. Then hatred of Chriſtians declared men to bee no Chriſtians at all, and can it now conſiſt with any new ſtampe of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? I conclude this point with that of Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Aug. de Bap. Cont. donat. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non habent dei Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, qui non diligunt eccleſiae unitatem, id eſt,</hi> they have not the love of God in them, who love not the unity of the Church of God, or the Church in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>In the next place let us looke with a tender eye of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19741:80"/> affection upon our mother Church, our <hi>Ieruſalem which is as a Citty that is compact together, whither the tribes goe up to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 122.3, 4. reade the gloſſe on the place, which runnes thus, By the artificiall joyning, and beauty of the houſes, hee meaneth the concord and love that was between the Cittizens: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, let us who are the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted members of the ſame Church in joynt affection, though in ſeverall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, endeavour all as one man to be of one heart and of one minde, as thoſe converts were, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32. Away, farre away with that factious love, which
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:19741:81"/> is as it were impropriated from the unity of the Church, and appropriated to I know not what ſelect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed brotherhood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by new-fangled liveries of religion.<note n="z" place="margin">This is to make Gods heritage a bird of divers (and therefore ſuperſtitious) colours, of which God complaines, Ierem. 12.9. whereas the Church ſhould be as an army with banners Cantic. 6.10 namely in which all hold together, and follow the ſame colours: ſo let all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low the unva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried enſigne of Chriſts Croſſe.</note> Why, I beſeech you (good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) have not wee all one father;<note n="a" place="margin">Quanto dignino fratres dìcuntur, qui unum patrem deum agnoſcant, qui unum ſpiritum biberunt ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, qui de uno utero ignorantiae ejuſdem, ad unam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem expiraverunt veritatis? Tertull. Apo cap <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Did not one God make us, Mal.</hi> 2.10. yea have wee not all one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well by redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as by creation? <hi>Thou Lord art our Father, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, Eſa.</hi> 63.16. Or be ſome baſtards and not ſonnes; Are we not <hi>fratres uterini,</hi> borne all of the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19741:81"/> ſame mother, the ſame Church, by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and by the ſame laver of regeneration, brought out of the common wombe of naturall ignorance, and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, into the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous light of the ſame divine truth and grace.</p>
            <p>Are wee not all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion in Charities judgement, nouriſhed with the ſame ſpirituall and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall foode? Did not our Saviour pay a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent price to redeeme us all? or laſtly, cannot one<note n="b" place="margin">Sumus corpus de conſcientia religionis, &amp; diſciplina ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, &amp; ſpei foedere Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in caetum &amp; quaſi manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facta deum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationibus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus. Tertull in Apolog. cap. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> Church hold us all in the ſame faith and hope, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame order of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline? or may not one heaven hold us all hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſure I am, it cannot hold
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19741:82"/> us, and our uncharitable opinions, or ſchiſmaticall practiſes: the ſeverall roomes there are for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall degrees of glory, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not for ſeverall facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; For if <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that is below, much more ſhee that is above is a Citty that is compact together, or, (as another tranſlation goeth) <hi>at unity in it ſelfe.</hi> The beauty of a body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke, or naturall, conſiſts not ſo much in the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of ſeverall parts; as in the Symmetry and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of all parts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So that hee that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces any part, deformes and marres all: even ſo the beauty and grace of Chriſts body, the Church
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:19741:82"/> conſiſts not in the abſolute perfection of ſome few parts, but in the relation which all the parts have the one to the other, in the communion of Saints.</p>
            <p>This makes Chriſts ſpouſe though<note n="c" place="margin">Cant. 1.5.</note> blacke (by the reliques of ſinne) yet comely by concord: and cauſeth all her actions to ſhine forth, though not without ſpot, yea in<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and order, as the Moone ſhines in her ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for the Church is faire as the<note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 6.10. ibid.</note> Moone, even in this life: but ſhe is cleare as the Sunne, onely in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Now they which break this order of the Church by ſchiſme, not onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:19741:83"/> the comelineſſe, but alter the very conſtitution of Chriſts body, and ſo diſpoſe it to finall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Divines prove God to be immortall, becauſe he is indiviſible: and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers prove both the greater world the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and the leſſer world man to be mortall; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both conſiſts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary elements; which by little aad little prepare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſſolution of the whole, which is then neare at hand when there is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of any of them in a notable meaſure, as the<note n="f" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.6.</note> overflowing of water de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the old world, and a<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Pet. 3.10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> Procellae in morem, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete Eraſmo. Sic mentio fit pluviae ignis. <hi>Gen. 19.24.</hi>
               </note> ſtorme or flood of fire ſhall overwhelme this:
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19741:83"/> or in the leſſer world, as redundancie of watry flegme, or fiery choler, ſoone brings us to our end of conſumption.</p>
            <p>But wee are united to Chriſt our head by faith, and to one another by love, neither doe petty er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours diſſolve the one band, nor petty quarrells breake the other. For then Chriſt ſhould bee as oft re-united to his members, and they to one another as<note n="h" place="margin">Maecenas, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties litem age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat cum uxore, &amp; toties amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem cum câ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinte grabat, ut dictum ſit. Hunc eſſe, qui uxorem millies duxit cum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam habuerit: Sen Epi. <hi>114.</hi> Idem lib. de providen. c. <hi>3.</hi> de ſcribit eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Maecena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teum, amoribus anxium &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſae uxoris quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridiana repudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deflentem.</note> 
               <hi>Maecenas</hi> was married to the ſame wife, as it were a new. But capitall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, which cut Chriſt the head of the Church quite off, or notorious ſchiſmes, which divide the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts of the ſpirituall
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19741:84"/> body, cauſe the ſpeedy ruine of a Church; For as the parts of a naturall ſo of the ſpirituall body, have no life in them, being ſevered from the head. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> may well ſtand, though a few ſtones drop out of her walls, and draw ſome that lye neareſt unto them out with them: but when the intire walls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be battered downe at once, then her curſe is neare, <hi>viz. that a ſtone ſhall not be left upon a ſtone.</hi> A Church may ſtill flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, though ſome buſie factioniſts ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from her, and draw a few ſectaries after them, whom ſhee may well miſſe and not want. But if he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:19741:84"/> ſhould be ſuffered to beate downe the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith, or ſchiſme, be able to deſtroy the wall of diſcipline, then beware of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> her curſe: <hi>Quod dij prius omen in ipſos Avertant hoſtes</hi>— Yet deſpiſe not petty contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or diſturbances; for oft a ſparke cauſes a flame. King <hi>Aſa</hi> died of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe onely in his feete, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> was choaked with a fly; and that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſoule of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> was let out at a bodkin hole. The leaſt diſcord that is, argues the want of ſome neceſſary degree of Charity,<note n="i" place="margin">Charitas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſemper in unitate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis: ſed non ſemper in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia conſiſtit; iuxta Aquin. Hinc Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, <hi>Rom. 14.1.</hi> &amp;c. infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum in fide, vult recipi (ſc. charitate fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna) ſed non ad dubias diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putationes: ſci. circa diverſas opiniones, de rebus non fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalibus.</note> which can cauſe unity of affection, amongſt them who differ in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:19741:85"/> And ſo much as there wants of Charity, ſo much there wants of holineſſe in the Church. For love, and onely love, fulfills the Law. But marke the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Habacucke</hi> his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, Chap. 1.3, 4. <hi>There are that raiſe up ſtrife and contention: Therefore the Law is ſlacked.</hi> The Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor of ſlacking is taken in the originall (as one well notes) from the pulſe of a man, which diſcovers the ſtate of his body to bee healthy, if it beate with an equall ſtroke, to be diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, if it beate violently; to grow weake, if it beate ſlowly and faintly; to be utterly gone, if it beate not all. So we may note, that
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:19741:85"/> where the Law of God is obſerved with equall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of impartiall love, (as in <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.5, 6.) there is ſpirituall found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde. Where the Law is proſecuted in ſome relations onely, &amp; in ſome parts thereof, and not in other: as in the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rather than in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, wherein conſiſteth the triall and exerciſe of love, there is a groſſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall diſtemper.</p>
            <p>Where the whole Law is ſlightly regarded, there Charity waxeth cold, or at leaſt, there is a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all luke-warmenes. Where the Law is utterly rejected and prophaned, there is an evident ſpirituall death in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:19741:86" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſinnes and treſpaſſes. By this rule, let every one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the ſtate of his ſoule, and bee a faithfull phiſitian to himſelfe, and ſo take care to bee a ſound member to the Church; which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe bee infected by him, and ſo by contagion brought to finall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the children that are corrupt (<hi>Eſaias</hi> 1.4.) are alſo corrupters, (as one tranſlation goeth) and ſo <hi>a ſeede of evill doers:</hi> even a viperous ſeede renting the womb that bare them, living by their mothers death, &amp; with<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act. 9.1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quaſi non aura aethercá, ſed ſanguine chriſtiano ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out ſlaughter againſt the Church <hi>Vae praegnanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus his diebus, Matth.</hi> 24.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19741:86"/> 19. woe unto the Churches that teeme in theſe latter dayes, and worſt with the monſters of faction and ſchiſme, with falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, of whom one ſaith, loe here is Chriſt, another loe there, <hi>v.</hi> 23. Againe <hi>v.</hi> 26. Behold he is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart (one ſaies) <hi>i. e.</hi> in a new unpeopled world, for this old world lyeth in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19. Another ſaith, Behold hee is in the ſecret chambers, perhaps, that is, in the conventicles of ſectaries at home. Now ought we not rather to wiſh unto a Church dry Paps, and a miſcarrying wombe; for which <hi>Hoſea</hi> praies, Chap. 9.14. then ſuch unhappy fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:19741:87"/> by which <hi>foecundius nequiora proveniunt</hi> (as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius Felix</hi> hath it in the dialogue) by which ſhee is fertile onely to bring forth evill to herſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the love of Chriſts Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note>In the fourth place my method ingages mee to commend unto you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the love of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, eſpecially of thoſe that are ſet over your ſoules in the Lord; For if the houſhold of faith bee eſpecially to be beloved, than of this houſhold, more eſpecially thoſe who are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, by whom yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. Love the Miniſters as the onely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inſtruments of the faith of Chriſt:<note n="l" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:19741:87"/> you</hi> brethren that yee acknowledge (as worthy of eſteeme, and not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne)<note n="m" place="margin">Ibid. v. 13.</note> 
               <hi>them which labour amongſt you; and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you: That you have them in ſingular love for their workes ſake: ſc.</hi> for the work of the Miniſtery. They which are ſet over you in the Lord, are your ſpirituall Fathers (as you heard) other Miniſters are but your fathers brethren. Very nature it ſelfe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you this morality to love your owne fathers before the neareſt of their kindred, and your fathers houſe before the houſe of any other. I have told you that Charity muſt be
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:19741:88"/> regular, and orderly, not prepoſterous. To ſpeake plainely, ſince there is a woe to the ſhepheard that leaveth his flocke, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.17. although (wee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) it be to feede others whom hee affecteth better than his owne; what ſhall wee thinke of the flocke that leave their ſhepheard, to run after ſome<note n="n" place="margin">Sic dictus a populo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ut notat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in lib. pr. Flori, Cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>poplico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> ſome Chaplaine of the multitude, ſome<note n="o" place="margin">Levita ille Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum cap. <hi>17.</hi> v. <hi>7, 8.</hi> &amp;c. Qui nullo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente Iſraelem (ver. <hi>6.</hi> erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundus victum &amp; veſtitum, vill ſuo mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio, (quod talipretio aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabatur) quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritabat. Aut qualis erat, cirumforane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ille mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, rumige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulus rabula, quiper imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum circulos, muliercularum que ſympoſia, contra Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymum decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat, ut teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur ipſe Hierony Epiſto. ad Domini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ideò Concilium Tridentinum vagos huiuſmodi praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantes conſulto prohibuit.</note> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Levite,</hi> ſome <hi>Sheba,</hi> like him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. that blowes the trumpet to faction in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and with the noiſe thereof, (as <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> with the ſound of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:19741:88"/> his Harpe, invited wilde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſts and ſtones to come unto him) drawes the whole country after him by the eares.<note n="p" place="margin">Tacit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> hiſt. pa. <hi>605.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apud ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem enim verba plurimum valent, bonaque ac mala, non ſuâ naturâ, ſed vocibus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio ſorum aeſtimantur.</hi> My Text mindes mee of Charity, and the mildeſt cenſure I can give is this: All theſe like ſheepe are gone aſtray: For they erre (ſurely) who forſake their owne fold and ſhepheard, to follow rather the voyce of any other. Tell me all yee that ſo uncharitably inveigh againſt double be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficed men, as againſt <hi>Polygamyſts.</hi> Becauſe an Elder muſt be the husband
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:19741:89" rendition="simple:additions"/> of one wife, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6. <hi>i. e.</hi> the paſtor of one Church, in<note n="q" place="margin">Ambr. Tom. <hi>4.</hi> l. de digni. ſa. ſerdota. cap. <hi>4.</hi> (in Tit. <hi>1.6.</hi> unius uxoris virum) Si ad ſuperficiem tantum literae reſpiciamus, prohibet diga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum ordinari Si vero ad al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorem ſenſum conſcendimus, inhibet Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum duas uſurpare ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias. Et ſi adhuc intror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus proſundio ra perſcrute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, monet, ne post Catholicum dogma, ſenſum inveniatur E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum habere hereticum, ſed Chriſtianem tantum Catholicam, &amp; orthodoxam aſſo iet, fidem, ut unius tantummodo uxoris &amp; Catholicae Eccleſiae vir, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus vocitetur.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, which in their ſenſe is the miniſter of one Pariſh: whereas with him the Catholicke Church is that one Church, and two Churches are two Faiths, Catholicke and Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. But the Apoſtle li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally forbids (ſaith hee) <hi>digamum Epiſcopum ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari,</hi> that is, that one that hath two wives ſhould be ordained a Biſhop. But I pray doe not theſe erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious courſes maintaine, or erect a new kind of <hi>lay plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities?</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:19741:89" rendition="simple:additions"/> Did not the ſame S. <hi>Paul</hi> propheſie againſt theſe pluralities, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12? The time will come when they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their owne luſts they ſhall heape to themſelves tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, having itching eares: Againe, all yee who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the diſpenſable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Paſtors from their cares as the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the Oſtrich in <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iob 39.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> that leaves her egges in the earth, and forgetteth that the foote may cruſh them. That is hardned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her young ones, as though they were not hers; and all this is becauſe (ſo farre perhaps they will follow the allegory) God
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:19741:90"/> hath deprived her of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Or, you that judge of all ſuch leaving the flocke, as <hi>Eliab</hi> judged of <hi>David</hi> his leaving of his few ſheepe in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.28, 29.</note> Namely that it is onely out of pride and haughtineſſe of heart: Whereas one may reply with <hi>David</hi> there: <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>What have I done, is there not a cauſe?</hi> what, have I done, are not the ſheepe left with a keeper, <hi>v.</hi> 20. And is there not a cauſe? have I not my leave and my meſſage given mee with <hi>David, ver.</hi> 17. Tell me I pray you is not your ſtraying from your owne Paſtors a new kind of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular non-reſidence. You
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:19741:90"/> run too and fro the land, as if there were<note n="t" place="margin">Amos 8.11.12.</note> a famine of the word; becauſe it is not dreſſed according to your faſtidious appetite.<note n="*" place="margin">Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call practiſes are to be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as well as ſchiſmaticall opinions; for factious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceipts doe recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally beget one the other, ſo that ſhee which is the daughter of ſchiſme, by prodigious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt; becomes againe the fruitfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Mater me ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, mater mox gignitur ex me.</hi>
               </note> Correct then this ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour by charity and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Waite upon thoſe whom God hath ſet over you,<note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 24.45.</note> 
               <hi>to give every one of you, your portion in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> As<note n="w" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> new borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the word, from thoſe breſts, which are made for your nouriſhment) that you may grow thereby. I am ſure you would have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to nurce their owne children, ſuppoſing the milke of any other breaſts, not ſo kindly. As for thoſe that urge unto you; the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:19741:91"/> example of the Iewiſh peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who left their blind guids the Scribs, &amp; Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, &amp;<note n="x" place="margin">Matth. 4.25.</note> came in great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all parts, to heare Chriſt preach; I will onely tell you that they ſpeake as wiſely on the extreame, as he in <hi>Zanchy</hi> on the other, who ſaid that if S. <hi>Paul</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſhould both preach at the ſame time in <hi>Geneva,</hi> he would not leave M. <hi>Calvin</hi> to heare S. <hi>Paul.</hi> For this man (it ſeemes) equalled in his judgement an ordinary paſtor with an Apoſtle, who had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate vocation from heaven, and was inſpired with the ſpirit of infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12. And the other debaſe
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:19741:91"/> in their opinion the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> into meere Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, that is in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours expoſition (<hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14.) <hi>blinde leaders of the blind,</hi> that muſt needs cauſe the people to<note n="y" place="margin">Pro. 29.18.</note> periſh for want of viſion. And on the other ſide they receive their new fangled tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers onely as the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> at the firſt entertained S. <hi>Paul</hi> as an Angel of God even as Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14. Whereas indeede every Miniſter ſhould bee received ſo: For wee are all Angels and Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of God,<note n="z" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> and ſtand in Chriſts ſtead, when we deliver Chriſts meſſage.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:19741:92" rendition="simple:additions"/> But as <hi>Abſalon</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements inſinuated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into the people, and ſtole away their hearts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 25.5, 6.</note> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cui ſimilis fere peromina Otho, de quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. l. <hi>1.</hi> hi Nec deerat: Otho protendens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num adorare vulgum iacere oſcula, et om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſerviliter pro dommatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Subdolum quoque hanc artem capian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di populum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribit pſalmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta. <hi>Pſal. 10.9, 10.</hi> Et Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus ipſe, <hi>2 Tim. 3. v. 5, 6, 7. Gal. 4 15.</hi>
               </note> So there are (I feare) colloguing Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, that creep firſt into mens houſes, and then into their boſomes, &amp; ſo ſteale away their harts by a new kind of ſacriledge, from their own Paſtors, &amp; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to leade them captive into errour: leaſt my phraſe tranſgreſſe the law of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, heare our Apoſtle (a man peſtered continually with ſuch falſe brethren:) they zealouſly affect you but not well They would exclude us, that you might affect them, Tis true, I muſt ſay it, though S. <hi>Pauls</hi> lot
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:19741:92"/> there <hi>v.</hi> 16. fal upon me for ſpeaking the truth: as <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> wiſhed that hee were judge in the Land, that he might do every man juſtice: ſo theſe men would raigne alone in the affection of the people, &amp; then every man ſhould ſurfet of Religion, untill perhaps they did complaine of Sermons, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Manna, <hi>Num.</hi> 11.6. Laſtly ſuppoſe <hi>Abſalon</hi> juſt, and innovators indeed zealous, yet away with rebellion, away with facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which bring greater diſturbance and confuſion with them, then the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; zeale of ſuch men, can poſſibly doe good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Wherefore
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:19741:93" rendition="simple:additions"/> S. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſo earneſt to cry downe all factious love to the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that he blames thoſe that make <hi>Cephas</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> yea or himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the head of faction, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. yea he is bold to reproove that zelot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who in any ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call humour cries out there, I am Chriſt. And I beſeech you what is the faction of Ieſuites at this day, but the monopolizing of Ieſus to themſelves? Wherefore Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> had a good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (how ever diverted) to change their title into Loyolites. For Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is no monopoly, to bee engroſſed into the hands
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:19741:93"/> of one ſociety: <hi>He brings common ſalvation, Iud.</hi> 3. the which hee extends to the univerſall Church, cauſing her by his Divine Charity to dwell in unity: that is, in himſelfe, for they dwell not in Chriſt, who dwell not in unity.</p>
            <p>The members of Chriſt lye not ſcattered like <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertus</hi> his limmes rent in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall peeces, by unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diviſions. Chriſt praies that his Diſciples may be one, as he and his Father are one, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.13. Now (then) I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by the name of our Lord Chriſt, that yee all ſpeake the ſame things and that there be no diviſions amongſt you, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:19741:94"/> 10. marke them which cauſe diviſions and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and avoyd them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. For by faire ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (<hi>Abſalon</hi>-like) they deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</p>
            <p>Once more. Muſt the Miniſters of Chriſt be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as ſpirituall Fathers? Then let your filiall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhew it ſelfe in<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> obeying their juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions: In following their good<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1.</note> examples: In bearing patiently their corrections and reproofes: by interpreting all their actions and words to the beſt: laſtly in being every way a comfort, and no way a vexation unto them. Let<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 10.12. 1 Pet. 4.8.</note> love cover their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:19741:94"/> though there bee a multitude of them, ſince<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 14.15.</note> they be men of like paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with you. I forget not what a bleſſing fell on <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Iaphet,</hi> for cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> father <hi>Noah</hi> his nakedneſſe, and what a curſe was inflicted on <hi>Cam</hi> and his poſterity, (<note n="g" place="margin">Quid filij meruere Quod tui Senec.</note> 
               <hi>Canaan</hi> being curſed for his ſake) for mocking at his fathers ſhame, though it were the effect of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſinne.</p>
            <p>In the judgement of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lerinenſis,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. conta. haereſ. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> they are the ſonnes of <hi>Sem,</hi> and <hi>Iaphet, Qui viri ſancti erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, nec adprobant, nec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt,</hi> who neither approve nor divulge the faults of one of Gods holy ones,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:19741:95"/> eſpecially of the Fathers of the Church. Such a ſonne of theirs was royall <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who profeſſed that if he ſhould take a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in any notorious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that hee would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cover him with his owne imperiall robe, then ſuffer him to bee an object of popular deriſion. They on the other ſide, are the ſonnes of <hi>Cham,</hi> (ſaith that excelleht Author) who do not onely neglect to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the infirmities of their ſpirituall Fathers, but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh them, eſpecially after their death, to vulgar ſcorne. We neede not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view antiquity to fetch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples thence in this kind, which are frequently ſet
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:19741:95"/> before our eyes. Each vulgar laicke doth now uſurpe the office of <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor, in Church and common wealth, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Church. (For men feare her authority leaſt) her cenſures are but <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> vaine threats to them; and her Prophets are but<note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 5.13.</note> winde; The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church are the <hi>Noahs,</hi> who in theſe dayes are made a<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.9.</note> ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle unto Angells and unto men, the bad I meane of both kindes. For the good of either kind, which love God, love Gods Miniſters. And we are glad, that not a few ſuch heare us this day, who know of theſe things, (I meane thoſe
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:19741:96"/> rude indignities which the Clergy dayly ſuffers) and before whom wee ſpeake boldly, as S. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 26.26.</note> before <hi>Agrippa,</hi> If there be any to whom wee are ſet forth as a ſpectacle even as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> his picture to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by all manner of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers on, from the head to the foote, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ending; wee are ready with <hi>Apelles</hi> to correct the cenſorious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> that preſumes to judge beyond his owne Art. Thou man of cenſure whoſoever thou art, doſt thou thinke that the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of Chriſt ſtand in the Pulpit, as the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at the barre, to expect judgement, yea variety or
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:19741:96"/> rather contrarietie of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to paſſe upon them? And doſt thou with the reſt of thy brethren and ſiſters, even <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and all the Craftſmen, with every ſilly woman,<note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.7.</note> laden with ſinne, captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto errours, wedded ſo ſurely to her owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and faction, that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive her divorce from them. Muſt theſe I ſay <hi>Et id genus omne,</hi> and all of the like kinde ſit upon their ſeverall ſeates of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as it were, and paſſe ſentence upon us whether right or wrong?</p>
            <p>One ſaith, perhaps with <hi>Feſtus,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 26.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath made the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:19741:97"/> beſide himſelfe, whereas another (it may be) thinkes him but an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man, becauſe hee can heare but few words of the Sermon, and ſcarce underſtand any, and ſo you muſt thinke that much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance hath, made him a learned cenſurer. Againe, ſuppoſe one accuſes the Preacher for lacke of the ſpirit of propheſie, which ſhould teach him what he ſhould preach in that houre, becauſe he hath not the gift of memory and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance. But if his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be ready, and his ſpeech fluent, then another is likely to judge him more full of words than matter, as if it were a ſigne that
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:19741:97"/> one is not laden with any great burden of propheſie, when he runs nimbly away with his matter: ſo that we cannot tell, whether wee go too faſt or too ſlow, for ſuch cenſurers, whoſe judgements, like fire and water overthrow one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and who like Chriſts accuſers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.56. ſeldome agree together. They will undertake to judge, who is a powerfull Preacher, and who is an edifying ſoule-ſaving Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour: when as for the moſt part of them, they know not what theſe very words, to preach, and to edifie meane, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe: yea though perhaps, with him that
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:19741:98" rendition="simple:additions"/> had lived 50. yeares under a preaching Miniſtery, they know not their<note n="o" place="margin">See an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this prodigious ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Pembles Sermon of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. pag. 17.18.</note> owne ſoule from their backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, or their God from a man like to themſelves. Moſt commonly they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake appearance for truth, ſeeming for being, noyſe for ſubſtance, earneſt and<note n="p" place="margin">Quis eſt qui in lintre loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ut ait ille apud Quintilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de quodam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nimico decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matore qui cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſuum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabat in partes omnes.</note> theatricall action on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide for zeale, bodily ſtrength for power of the ſpirit, memory for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and faction for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If any here have thus preſumed not onely to be teachers of the Law, as it is 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. but alſo judges of teachers, not knowing what the ſpeake, or whereof they affirme: No more than <hi>Balaams</hi>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:19741:98"/> beaſt underſtood what ſhe ſaid, when ſhee reprooved with humane voyce the madneſſe of the Prophet; (Onely here is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene them) that God opened her mouth: but theſe in effect open their mouthes againſt God, with thoſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4. I would wiſh them to confeſſe their fault unto God ingeniouſly, for the time paſt, in <hi>Davids</hi> words: Wee have beene fooliſh and ignorant, even as a beaſt before thee: And for the time to come, I intreate them to take <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons,</hi> advice, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. viz. to be more ready to heare Gods word taught by thoſe that have firſt
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:19741:99" rendition="simple:additions"/> learned it themſelves, then to offer the ſacrifice of fooles, <hi>i. e.</hi> (to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the words to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) to give a raſh cenſure of what is ſpoken. This is a ſtrange fire of falſe zeale, which muſt not burne the ſacrifice or incenſe that God will accept of: If thou wilt preſent an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that God ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, take S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his direction: <hi>Zelum tuum inflammet charitas, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met ſcientia;</hi> Let it bee a burnt offering of zeale, made ready for the Lord by knowledge, and ſet on fire by love: For this love inflame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowledge to the deſire of good, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge directing love to the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:19741:99"/> performance of the ſame, fulfill the Law.</p>
            <p>So I addreſſe my ſpeech for a concluſion by way of briefe but earneſt exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note n="*" place="margin">5. Of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall love of Chriſtians in what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſocieties ſoever they live together.</note> of you of the Laitie alſo to mutuall love in the Lord Ieſus,<note n="q" place="margin">Eccles. 12.11.</note> at leaſt to the increaſe and continuance thereof. Suppoſing I may ſay with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. &amp; 10. <hi>As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brotherly love, yee neede not that I write (or ſpeake) unto you, for yee your ſelves are taught of God to love one another: And indeede yee doe it.</hi> Yet muſt I goe on with S. <hi>Paul</hi> there. <hi>But we beſeech you brethren, that yee increaſe more and more, and that yee ſtudy to be quiet, &amp;c. v.</hi> 11. Although then
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:19741:100"/> you be in charity already with one another, yet let the<note n="q" place="margin">Eccl. 12.11.</note> words of the wiſe (even of the ſpirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) bee as goads (to drive you forwards in this duty) and as nailes faſtned by the maſters of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies (to fix this grace the ſurer in your mindes) which are given from one ſhepheard <hi>ſc.</hi> Chriſt Ieſus the chiefe ſhepheard and Byſhop of our ſoules. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I beſeech you in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus: Above all things (farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all by-reſpects of ſelfe love) <hi>have fervent charity amongſt your ſelves,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. To this purpoſe <hi>Conſider one another to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke to love, and to good
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:19741:100" rendition="simple:additions"/> workes</hi> (the effects of love) <hi>not forſaking the aſſemblings of your ſelves,</hi> (like bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren together in vnity) <hi>as the manner of ſome is, Heb.</hi> 10.24, 25. <hi>And be at peace among your ſelves,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Shewing your love to one another, by your agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment together. For hatred ſtirreth up strife, Prov.</hi> 10.12. <hi>And it is onely pride that begetteth this hatred, for onely by pride commeth contention, Prov.</hi> 13.10. <hi>But with the well adviſed is wiſedome,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> there: <hi>And love, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers all ſinnes</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> hath it) <hi>Ib. ſc. Prov.</hi> 10.12. is the fraight of heavenly wiſedome. For this wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is <hi>peaceable, gentle, eaſie
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:19741:101" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be intreated, Iam.</hi> 3.17. yea ſhe is ready not only to accept, but to offer agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For there v. 18. <hi>not onely the fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is ſowne in peace, but it is alſo of them that make peace.</hi> So then my brethren, not onely have love, and bee at peace, when love and peace are preſented unto you, but alſo<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 14.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perſequimur charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> Follow after or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1. And likewiſe as <hi>David</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaere pacem &amp; ſequere eam: i. e.</hi> ſeeke peace and follow it<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pagnin. in Lex. Qui tamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quaere, non verbis ſolum, &amp; interrogatione, hoc enim est</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſed conatu, &amp; studi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:19741:101"/> hoc enim</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſignificat;</hi> The word in the originall intimates, that wee ſhould ſeeke peace; not onely in<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 55 21.</note> words by inquiring after it, with an is it peace O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu, but in deedes alſo, by ſerious ſtudy and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to attaine it. Although your ſoules with <hi>Davids,</hi> have long dwelt with thoſe that are enemies to peace, and perſecute it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrife and faction, yet doe you ſtill (with <hi>David</hi>) purſue peace, to imbrace and poſſeſſe it: Alas, love and peace like riches,<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> make themſelves wings and flye away, like an Eagle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven: And like a bird eſcaped, they are hardly caught and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:19741:102"/> brought backe againe: O then you that enjoy them, hold them faſt, as <hi>Iacob</hi> held the Angell that they may bleſſe you ere they goe away; or rather that they may not depart at all: So that either your prayers and endeavours may returne into your owne boſomes, and make you happy in your owne conſciences: or elſe may all ſo take effect abroad, and make you happy in the fruit thereof among your brethren. For truth it ſelfe hath ſayd, that <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers, Mat.</hi> 5.9. that is, not onely they which effect, but they alſo which heartily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour peace.</p>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:19741:102"/>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Col. 3.12.</note>
               <hi>Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) bowells of mercies, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekenes, long-ſuſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forbearing one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrell againſt any: Even as Christ forgave you, ſo alſo doe yee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And above all things put on Charity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 14.</note> 
               <hi>which is the bond of perfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And let the peace of God (and ſo conſequently,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the God of peace) rule in your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare the concluſion of the whole matter w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I have delivered unto you on my Text, and that you ſhall have from S. <hi>Auguſtine,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:19741:103"/> Si non vacat, &amp;c.</hi> If thou haſt no leaſure to turne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the leaves of holy writ, hold faſt Charity: And in her thou ſhalt finde all knowledg; ſo thou ſhalt retaine in thy minde, both what thou haſt learned in Scripture, and alſo what thou haſt not learned. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon Charity all the Law and the Prophets de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. In that which thou underſtandeſt Charity is evident; in that which thou underſtandeſt not, Charity lyeth hidden. He therefore holds faſts that which is manifeſt, and that which is abſtruſe in Gods word, who keepes Charity in his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Charity is the bond
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:19741:103"/> of affections, without which the rich man is poore, and with which the poore man is rich. How great is ſhe? The ſafeguard of the ſoule, the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of knowledge, the fruit of faith, the wealth of the needy, the life of dying men. Shee alone is not troubled with other mens felicitie, for ſhee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieth not. Shee alone is not lifted on high with her owne proſperity, for ſhee is not puffed up. Among reproaches ſhee is ſecure, in the midſt of hatred ſhee is kind. Amongſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells ſhe is gentle, amongſt treacheries ſhee is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Therefore ſhe beares all things in this preſent
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:19741:104"/> life, becauſe ſhee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all things concerning the life to come. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever more abundant good then my ſpeech can utter, you ſhall finde out in the commendation of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let it appeare in your lives: Thus<note n="w" place="margin">Ipſiſsima Auguſt. verba ſunt Tom. <hi>10.</hi> pag. <hi>232.</hi> ſerm. <hi>39.</hi> de Temp Si non vacat omnes paginas Scripturarum evolvere, tene Charitatem, et in ea invenies omnem ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. Ita tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, quod in Scriptura didicisti, tenebis etiam quod non diduſti, Quia â Charitate tota lex et prophete pendent, In eo quod intelligis, charitas patet, in eo quod non intelligis, Charitas latet. Ille itaque tenet, &amp; quod patet, &amp; quod latet in divinis ſermonibus, qui charitatem tenet in moribus. Vinculum eſt mentium, ſine qua dives pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſt, &amp; cum qua pauper dives eſt. Quanta eſt ista? Animarum ſalus, ſcientiae ſolidamentum, fidei fructus, divitiae pauperum, vita moricatium. Sola eſt, quam fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas aliena nompremit, qui a non aemulatur Sola eſt quam faelicitas ſua non extollit, quia non inflatur. Inter opprobria ſecitra eſt. Inter odia benefica eſt. Inter iras placida eſt; Inter inſidias innocens. Ideo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerat omnia, &amp;c. ibid.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teaches you how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate by your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, that Charity is the fulfilling of the Law. Now
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:19741:104" rendition="simple:additions"/> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> having exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you to Charity; Next let S. <hi>Gregory</hi> dehort you from ſtrife and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, <hi>Cur. pastora. part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>admo.</hi> 24. <hi>Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſeminantes jurgia, quam multipliciter pecant, qui dum unam nequitiam perpetrant ab humanis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus canctas ſimul virtutes eradicant. In uno enim ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo innumera peragunt, quia ſeminando diſcordiam, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem quae virtutum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium mater eſt, extingunt, i. e.</hi> Let thoſe (on the other ſide) that ſow contention (amongſt Chriſtian bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) conſider how mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold their offence is, who by committing one ſinne roote out all vertues what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:19741:105"/> out of mens hearts: for in one evill they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many, becauſe they deſtroy Charity, which is the mother of all vertues. And thus men of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, demonſtrate by their lives, that uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the violation of the whole Law of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhut up all with one pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall exhortation, and one fervent prayer; both learned of our Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul.</hi> The firſt is,<note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 2. V. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1, &amp;c. <hi>If there bee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 2.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Fulfill yee my joy, that ye may be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of one minde. Let nothing be done through
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:19741:105"/> ſtrife or vaine glory, &amp;c. Looke not every man to his owne things, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 4.</note> 
               <hi>And this I pray</hi> (with S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. V. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9, <hi>&amp;c. That your love may abound yet more and more, in knowledge and in all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 10.</note> 
               <hi>That yee may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove things that are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent (which are the things of Charity,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. <hi>and Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ibid) that you may bee ſincere and without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, until the day of Chriſt. Being filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 11.</note> 
               <hi>which are by Ieſus Chriſt, unto the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and praiſe of God.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="204" facs="tcp:19741:106"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 98. line. 18. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 118. l. 23. for <hi>incundiſſima</hi> r. <hi>incundiſſimi.</hi> p. 144 l. 21. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 145. l, 22. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 152. l. 15. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>In the Margent.</head>
            <p>PAg. 69. l. 20. for <hi>tantum,</hi> r. <hi>tantam.</hi> p. 80. l. 5. for <hi>unam,</hi> r. <hi>unum.</hi> p. 96. l. 29. for <hi>flax,</hi> r. <hi>fax.</hi> p. 125. l. 2. r. <hi>potsſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non aſtrictam uni, &amp;c.</hi> p. r 41. l. 10. for <hi>ille fuit reverentiae,</hi> r. <hi>illi fuit reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia.</hi> p. 154. l. 27. for <hi>unam,</hi> r. <hi>unum.</hi> p. 155. l. 4 for <hi>Deam,</hi> r. <hi>Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19741:106"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
